<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Light vanquishing darknesse. Or a vindication of some truths formerly declared, from those aspersions which have been (by reason of some misapprehensions) cast upon them; now published for the satisfaction and benefit of others. With a preambular epistle to all sorts of men. As also a parcell of good counsell, if you can take it. / By Captain Francis Freeman, a late member of the army.</title>
            <author>Freeman, Francis.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84893</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2129</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E615_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206543</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865674</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865674</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117922</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84893)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117922)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 94:E615[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Light vanquishing darknesse. Or a vindication of some truths formerly declared, from those aspersions which have been (by reason of some misapprehensions) cast upon them; now published for the satisfaction and benefit of others. With a preambular epistle to all sorts of men. As also a parcell of good counsell, if you can take it. / By Captain Francis Freeman, a late member of the army.</title>
                  <author>Freeman, Francis.</author>
                  <author>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, Baron, 1612-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 66 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes a letter by Thomas Fairfax.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octo: 29".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117922:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LIGHT VANQUISHING DARKNESSE.</p>
            <p>OR A vindication of ſome Truths formerly declared, from thoſe aſperſions which have been (by reaſon of ſome miſapprehenſions) caſt upon them; now publiſhed for the ſatisfaction and benefit of others.</p>
            <p>With a preambular Epiſtle to all ſorts of Men. As alſo a Parcell of good Counſell, if you can take it.</p>
            <p>By Captain FRANCIS FREEMAN, a late member of the Army.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>After that which men call hereſie, will I worſhip the God of my Fathers, The ſpirituall man judgeth all things, yet he himſelf is judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of no man.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed in the year 1650.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:117922:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117922:2"/>
            <head>An Epiſtle to all ſorts of Men.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O All Chriſtian Kings, Queenes, Princes, Prieſts, Rulers and governours; and to all that love the King; and to all that are in authority under Him, of what degree, or in what condition or ſtation ſoever: whether Papiſt, Proteſtant, Presbyterian, Antinomian, Independant, Anabaptiſt, Seeker &amp;c. Both high and low, rich and poor, from the loweſt form to the higheſt; and ſo to all thoſe that have paſt through all formes, and are above them, <hi>that worſhip God, not on this mountain, nor at Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, but in ſpirit and truth.</hi> Neither can they deſcend ſo low, as to look back, to ſee God in an ordinance, or in any of theſe formes, or in any other forme; but ſee him purely as he is, <hi>Jehovah Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him;</hi> who ſee him in the cloudes, and in the ſun, who ſee him in the heavens, and in the firmament, <hi>for the heavens declare his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> &amp;c. who ſee him in all things above and below, and in every thing that hath a being in the whole Creation. <hi>Theſe things</hi> I <hi>write unto you, concerning them that ſeduce you; but the anointing which you have received of him, abideth in you, and teacheth you of all things, and is truth, and is no ly</hi> &amp;c. and as the Son of the <hi>bond-woman,</hi> perſecutes the Son of the <hi>free-woman,</hi> ſo every form is a perſecutor. And he that is under any of theſe forms, is ready to perſecute him that is above them, or below them, or contrary to him in judgement: But the ſon of the <hi>free-woman,</hi> is free from perſecuting any. And as there are diverſities of formes; and that every form is a perſecutor, ſo there are diverſities of degrees in every form, ſome high, ſome low, ſome rich, ſome poor, yet all in the Spirit. The higheſt degree of Papiſts, are almoſt Proteſtants, the higheſt degree of Proteſtants, are almoſt Presbyterians, the higheſt degree of Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians, are almoſt Antinomians, the higheſt degree of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomians,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117922:3"/>are almoſt Independants, the higheſt degree of Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendants, are almoſt Anabaptiſts, and the Anabaptiſts, are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Seekers, and the Seekers are at a ſtand: Although they are in the uppermoſt form, yet they know that there is ſomething a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all theſe formes, which they have not yet found, but are in a ſeeking condition, yet their ſtrength is to ſtand ſtill, till God drawes them up into himſelf; then ſhall they be of that rich fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of love, they ſhall attain to that high pitch of perſection, as to be of Gods own familie, God dwelling in the midſt of them, and they living continually in and upon him. For he that dwels in love, dwels in God, and God in him. Now all thoſe that are of this rich family of love; are above all formes, types, and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes; And are in reallitie, truth, ſubſtance: they need not that any man teach them; they are all taught of God, they are entred into their reſt, they ceaſe from their labors, as God did from his, and their works follow them; there is a continuall Sabbath to them; God is their Sabbath in them. All externall formes of ſelf-duties and performances, as of duties of faſting and humiliation, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of prayer &amp;c. all are turned into praiſes and thanksgivings, Halelujahs. Now there is nothing but mirth in them, there is a continual ſinging of birds in them, chirping ſweetly, in a ſweet harmony of ſoul-raviſhing delightful muſick.</p>
            <p>Reader, I ſhall give thee to underſtand, that this enſuing Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, hath been almoſt ready for the preſſe a long time ſince, and caſt aſide, having no thoughts of publiſhing it. But ſeeing tis the Fathers pleaſure, I ſhould declare my judgement to the whole world, I could not but doe it; partly to vindicate the truth, and the rather, becauſe ſome members of the Armye (whom I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive have not yet paſt through the third forme) have a prejudice againſt me, as if a child that hath not learn'd his primar: ſhould undertake to teach him that hath learned his Accidence or Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and is perfect in them. And as if the pooreſt Schollar in the loweſt forme, ſhould undertake to seach the beſt Schollar in the uppermoſt form in the School. And partly to diſcover the folly and weakneſſe of theſe mine accuſors. I ſhall therefore give you a breife marrative both of the manner, and ſubſtance of our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, for which they had a prejudice againſt me, which is as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:117922:3"/>
            <p>Firſt, I had ſome diſcourſe with <hi>Capt. Lieu. Leigh,</hi> and <hi>Cornet Friend,</hi> touching forms in the worſhip and ſervice of God, and touching ſeveral adminiſtrators or diſpenſations that the people were under; and my poſition was, that God might be ſeen in the loweſt form or miniſtration, and that I had now no prejudice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the perſon of any man, that was above me, or below me, and that I ſaw God in all things and in every thing that had a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the whole creation: working in the creature, according to the ſeveral diſpenſations wherein he had placed them. Then the Cornet asked me, <hi>whether I ſaw God in the Table-board or in the Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick?</hi> My anſwer was yea, I ſaw him in both. Then he went about to prove (in a Syllogiſticall way) that the Table-board was dead, the Candle-ſtick was dead, and God was a living God. Therefore I could not ſee him there in the Tableboard, but I might ſee him in the Work-man-ſhip of it; and with all demanded of me, whether I ſaw him eſſentially in the Table-board, my anſwer was I made no difference, or diſtinction betwixt his eſſence, and his being, for they were one, and that God was every where, and in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and in every thing. He was both <hi>omnipotent, omnipreſent, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſcient,</hi> and his eſſential will was himſelf, his power was himſelf, his wiſdome was himſelf. Then ſaid the Cornet, Capt. <hi>Freeman,</hi> you ſay that you have no prejudice againſt the perſon of any man, are all men alike with you? what do you think of drunkards? my anſwer was, yea, they were all one to me, although in time paſt, I had a prejudice againſt ſome, when I was under forms, yet now I had not; for a drunkard, or any other man that was addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to any other ſin or vice (which all men are ſubject unto) could not leave it till God call'd them from it. Then we ſpake ſomething concerning the uſe of Ordinances; which I told them that I was not againſt the uſe of them, nor any man that was on ſuch a diſpenſation, for he was in the ſame ſtation wherein God had placed him, and ſo we brake of our diſcourſe for that time: but it ſeemed to me, that they were ſomewhat troubled at it.</p>
            <p>Now the next time we met together, we had ſome farther diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe touching ordinances; and to my thinking (before we par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted), they were very well ſatisfied, for we parted upon very faire terms, and I went up into my Chamber, where I was not long,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117922:4"/>before I had ſome thoughts of writing an Epiſtle to all ſorts of men, and ſo call'd for a Pen, Ioke and Paper, and began to write, but before I had wrote three lines, they came to me again, and I told them what I was about, and that I was writing an Epiſtle to all ſorts of men, that were under ſeverall diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or Miniſtration, and ſo fell into Diſcourſe againe, ſpent ſome time in it; and all this time they were very merry and pleaſant with me, in ſo much that I could not conceive they had any prejudice againſt me, or any deſign to advance their own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, which I ſhall referre to you to judge. And ſo we parted for that night, and went to bed, and the next morning I wrote the former part of this Epiſtle, and ſhewed it to them, but it did appear to me, that it was not well reſented by them; For, in a very ſhort time after, they made ſome complaint to Colonel <hi>Okey</hi> of ſome ſtrange points which I ſhould hold (as they ſaid) which occaſioned ſome diſpute amongſt us, in the preſence of one Capt. <hi>Smith</hi> and others,</p>
            <p>Now the Colonel meeting me at <hi>Bedford</hi> (with ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther officers of his Regiment) told me that he had heard of ſome ſtrange opinions I ſhould hold, but never had any diſcourſe with me, as to know what they were; Therefore he deſired to propound ſome queſtions unto me. My anſwer was, that I ſhould be very free to anſwer to any queſtion that he ſhould propound unto me; ſo that it might be done in a way of love; which he promiſed it ſhould. So he propounded this queſtian firſt, what I thought of the uſe of ordinances? my anſwer was, that all thoſe that were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any of them, or in the uſe of any of them; that it was their duty to be obedient unto them, till God call'd them to a higher miniſtration. And that I liked them well, that were zealous in the performance thereof, for I did beleeve they had ſome comfort in the uſe of them.</p>
            <p>The Second queſtion was, what <hi>I</hi> thought of the Scriptures, and whether I did acknowledge the Scriptures to be the word of God? my anſwer was, that it is the written word of God, the Prophets, and Apoſtle were the Penmen, and that it was my dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practiſe, to make uſe of the Bible called the Scriptures, when opportunity ſerved; and I told them that every Scripture is a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, untill it be made known to us, or revealed in us; and ſo it
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117922:4"/>comes to be above that Scripture without us; for, it is ſaid to be a hidden myſtery, <hi>to them that periſh: but the power of God unto ſalvation to every one that beleeves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then by this time they all came about me like Bees (as the <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt</hi> ſaith) <hi>they kept me up on every ſide, they kept me up I ſay on every ſide</hi> &amp;c. one catcht at me, and another catcht at me, inſomuch that I ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſired them to forbear any further diſcourſe; for I ſaw that they lay in wait for me; and as it did appear to us afterwards, that they had laid a ſnare to entrap me, and katch me into their own Net, which they cunningly had laid. But I was very cautious and wary how to ſpeak to them, and for this reaſon which I gave them, that I might ſpeak ſomething in anſwer to their queſtions that they might not well bear; for; ſaid I, that which may be a truth to me, may not be a truth to you, and yet a truth in it ſelf. The Word of God, which is God in his Word, written in me, is more to me then the whole Book of the Scriptures, both of the old and new Teſtament; for what is it, without it be unſealed and the Book opened? and yet I can aſſure you, I priſe it, at as high a rate, as any of you all can doe; but if ſo be you ſhould ask a Child of ſeven years old, what booke it is, and lay it before him, he will ſay it is the Bible, or peradventure, he will tell you tis the Scripture, why? becauſe he hath been told ſo: but if ſo be, I know the word of God, which is, God in his word, be written in me; then I know aſſuredly, that is the word of God, becauſe it is ſo manifeſted unto me. But how ſhall we know this of a truth, ſaid Cornet <hi>Friend,</hi> how may this appear to us? My an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer was, that the witneſſe of the ſpirit, did bear witneſſe with my ſpirit: and that I had certain evidences, and demonſtrations of the ſpirit of God working in my ſpirit; and that I ſaw a glorious change in me, ſince I had paſt through all theſe formes; or mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteations, which I had formerly been under. I told them like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, That I had bin a Papiſt, Proteſtant, Presbyterian, Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mian, Independant, Anabaptiſt, Seeker &amp;c. But I gave God thanks, I had paſt through them all; and that Scripture was ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in me, which was a promiſe made by Chriſt, that he would <hi>put his laws in our minds, he would writ them in our hearts,</hi> and he would be to us a God, and we ſhould be to him a people. Which lawes are written in my heart, and have made me conformable in obedience
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117922:5"/>to his will, and this law being written in my heart; is far above any law without me. As for example, the Scriptures containe in them divers precepts, as in the decalogue. <hi>Thou ſhall do no murder, Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery, Thou ſhalt not ſteale, Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe &amp;c.</hi> We ſee this law, we reade it, and yet we break it, we cannot keep it, Why? becauſe we ſee and reade no more but the bare literal expreſſions, and is without us. But if God comes in in power, and commands me from within, either to doe or not to doe, then I cannot breake it, but I muſt keepe it, and that from a Principle of love from within.</p>
            <p>Then came in Capt. <hi>Neale</hi> and one Mr. <hi>Easton,</hi> who being no ſooner in the Room, but Col. <hi>Okey</hi> (in a ſeeming merry way) took Captain <hi>Neale</hi> by the ſhoulder, and thruſt him to me; uſing theſe very expreſſions. That he would be on my ſide, for he was of my judgement. To which Capt. <hi>Neale</hi> anſwered, that he thought he ſhould, although we were the weaker ſide. Then Lieut. <hi>Cheeſe</hi> ſpake ſomething in reference to our former diſcourſe. Cap. <hi>Neal</hi> asked me, whether I would anſwer him, or whether he ſhould? So I deſired him to anſwer, (being willing to be quit of any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcourſe) for thoſe reaſons before mentioned, in that I found them to lie in wait for me. Then Capt. <hi>Neale</hi> anſvvered clearly to the point, which he is very well able to give an account of. Then Leiut. <hi>Cheeſe</hi> replyed; (and all this while there ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no prejudice outwardly againſt either of us) and Mr. <hi>Eaſton</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered to his reply, and undertook the diſcourſe; but before he had done ſpeaking, Colonel <hi>Okey</hi> deſired him to make repetition of what he had ſaid, which he did; then the Colonel took firſt a preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice againſt him; and uſed him very uncivilly, and unſeemingly, in the preſence of all that were there; for he bad him go forth of the room for he was a dangerous fellow, and not ſit ſociety for any honeſt man, and this was for nothing, but declaring his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But <hi>Mr. Eaſton</hi> deſired to ſpeake farther to the point, and that there might be a right underſtanding betwixt them. No ſaid the Colonel, and bad him hold his tongue, and get him forth, for he had ſomething to ſpeake to ſome Officers of his Regiment; and ſo fell very foule upon Captain <hi>Neale,</hi> with bitter language, and then upon me and told us, he would roote us out of his Regiment, or elſe we ſhould root out him, and commanded us to be gone: which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117922:5"/>command was immediately obeyed.</p>
            <p>Now I ſhall appeal to all godly conſcientious men, to judge whether this diſcourſe was in a way of love, or not, according to his promiſe and engagement; When as they did (as it were) force me to diſcourſe, and to anſwer to all their queſtions; yet I am ſure they have no advantage againſt me therby. But to proceed, the next morning I met with Capt. <hi>Smith,</hi> who told me, that he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked our diſcourſe very well: but ſhook his head, &amp; ſaid, that he was very ſorry to hear, and ſee ſuch miſcarriages and <hi>claſhings againſt us.</hi> Now the ſame morning the Colonel ſent for Mr. <hi>Cloſe</hi> (Chaplian to his Regiment) and diſcharged him, becauſe (as he ſaid) he was of our judgement. Mr. <hi>Cloſe</hi> deſired to know what might be laid to his charge, to be ſo caſtoff, without a <hi>Councell of Warre,</hi> and that he might know his accuſers: The Colonel told him, that he had preacht dangerous doctrine, and held dangerous tenets: therefore he ſhould no longer continue in his Regiment. Then Capt. <hi>Neale</hi> and I deſired him, that we might all three be tryed at a <hi>Councel at Warre,</hi> for we conceived all our caſes were alike, but that would not be granted: but howſoever; The Colonel then told Mr. <hi>Cloſe</hi> that he might ride in any Troop of the Regiment, but not as <hi>Chaplain;</hi> to which he anſwered, that if he were not fit to be <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain</hi> to the Regiment, he was not fit to ride in any Troop. Then I deſired to know of him, what he had againſt me, or what he could lay to my charge? His anſwer was, that I held dangerous tenets, that I denyed the Scriptures, and that I made God the author of ſin. Which I denyed, and withall did aske him, where ever he heard me ſay ſo in poſitive terms? He anſwered no, but that I did as good in effect. And thus you may ſee, he would draw concluſions according to his own fancy. Therefore give me leave to draw one concluſion according to their practiſe, which is this, that if God juſtifies their actions (which they believe he doth) then is God the Author of ſinne. But no more of this, for I am very Ioath to digreſſe; but to proceed. The Colonel did likewiſe rip up the old ſore at <hi>Taunton,</hi> and told me that I ſaid I was Chriſt, and that if it had not been for him, I had been ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhier'd for it; which argues abundance of weakneſſe in him, or malice towards me, he knowing that I had clearly anſwered to their charge, and that Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> had moved the Generall for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117922:6"/>for the wrongs done unto me. Then Cornet <hi>Friend</hi> laid this to my charge; that I ſhould ſay that I had as live keep a Drunkard company as any other man, which I denyed, neither did I indeed ſpeak it at all upon any other tearmes, then as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned. You ſay you have no prejudice againſt the perſon of any man (ſaid he) then I pray tell us, <hi>wherefore you keep up your ſword?</hi> My anſwer was to maintain our juſt rights and priviledges which is our birth-right, <hi>&amp; to relieve the oppreſſed,</hi> &amp; not intentively to kill any man; and with all did demand this queſtion of him, <hi>wherefore he kept up his ſword?</hi> His anſwer was, to kill the Caveliers, then ſaid I, <hi>you are a man of blood, you kill all the day long,</hi> and I had as live keep a drunkard company, as keep you company: and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all I told them, that they might ſee, that I was both ready and willing to do the States the beſt ſervice I could (as I had formerly done) and that I was willing, to go with my whole Troop, for the ſervice of <hi>Ireland,</hi> which if I had not been willing, then I had been disbanded upon that Account without any more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe.</p>
            <p>And thus I have given you a plenarie deſcription (according to truth) both of the manner, and alſo the matter and ſubſtance of our diſcourſe; and if ſo be, it ſhould be denyed, I can prove it by Capt. <hi>Smith</hi> and others. And now I ſhall ſhew you, how they have ſhot their poyſoned arrows, even <hi>bitter words againſt me,</hi> and have ſpit their poyſon at me, <hi>to render me</hi> as odious, as they can poſſibly: and all to drive on their own deſignes, and ſet up their intereſts. For here you ſhall find (if it may come to a tryall) that the Cap. <hi>Leiut.</hi> gap'd after my command as much as ever any ungracious ſon did gape after his Fathers death, that he might inherit his poſſeſſions, as may appear by his often, and earneſt ſolicitations to the Col. that he would give him my Troop, if he could get Col. <hi>Rich</hi> his letter, and Col. <hi>Harriſons</hi> letter to him. Then Cornet <hi>Friend</hi> looked for preferment too; &amp; Quartermaſter <hi>Gilmore</hi> gap'd after my <hi>Cornets</hi> place, who went for the Service of <hi>Ireland;</hi> and indeed I wrote my letter in his behalf to my Col: That he might have it; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding (I knew) that he had done ſome good officers for me. And theſe are my accuſers, who (by their falſe and ſcandalous ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations) have cauſed the Col: (he being very apt to hear with other men ears, ſee with other mens eyes, and to ſpeak the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117922:6"/>of other men) eſpecially to drive on their own deſignes according to their hearts deſire. And as for Quarter-maſter <hi>Gilmore,</hi> he let fall theſe very expreſſions to his Land-lady (where he quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred at <hi>Rowell</hi> in <hi>Northampton-ſhire</hi>) that there were but few officers in the Army of his Captains judgement, and that <hi>Crumwell</hi> was now gon into <hi>Ireland,</hi> therefore they could new model the Army at their pleaſure.</p>
            <p>And truly for my part, this did evidently appear to me, that their intentions were no leſſe, but that they would root out all of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, that were contrary to them in judgement; for I met with a Colonel of the Army in <hi>Weſtminster-Hall,</hi> who did (as good in effect) ſay ſo much to me; for he told me, that I countenanced <hi>blaſphemie,</hi> and if ſo be I had been a Captain in his Regiment, he would have done no leſſe then my Col. did: and that there would ſuddainly be a charge drawn up againſt me, but I (knowing my own innocency) told him, that I did not value a chip, any charge that could be brought in againſt me: and truly for my part (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived) his very countenance did import much wrath and bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſpirit againſt me, although he ſcarce ever knew me, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver exchanged three words with me before. But what he had, (it ſeemed) he received it from Col. <hi>Okey;</hi> or from ſome ſcandalous papers which were ſpread abroad by him, which was ground e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for his anger towards me: for here you ſhall ſee, <hi>hand over head, without due examination;</hi> they will judge and condemn, and ſpeak purely one anothers language, and all to advance their own intereſts. But what they account <hi>blaſphemie,</hi> I know not; but I am ſure, I have caſhier'd many of my Souldiers for ſwearing and drunkenneſſe, and have ſharply reproved others, for any kind of vice whatſoever, that hath come within the compaſſe of <hi>my</hi> cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance, and that I ſhall appeal to theſe ſeveral places where we have bin quartered any time this fifteen moneths and upwards.</p>
            <p>We were quartred eighteen weeks at <hi>Buckinghame</hi> and <hi>Brackly,</hi> three and twenty weeks at Saint <hi>Neots</hi> and <hi>Kimbolton,</hi> five weeks at <hi>Keter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>Rowel,</hi> fourteen weeks at <hi>Colebrooke</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge,</hi> and eight weeks more at S. <hi>Neots</hi> &amp; <hi>Kimbelion,</hi> before our march into <hi>Scotland.</hi> All which time, the <hi>people</hi> in theſe ſeverall places have had ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent experience of us: and are able and willing if occaſion ſhould ſerve, to give a very good teſtimony of our civil behaviour and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117922:7"/>carriage towards them, and I dare be bold to ſpeak it; that they are as willing and ready to give us entertainment, as any troope in the Army, and no diſparigement to any.</p>
            <p>And now you ſhall ſee more of my Col. dealings towards me (my Cornet and three and twenty of my men, being gone for the ſervice of Ireland, under Capt. <hi>Barrington</hi>) how he took ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage thereby, notwitſtanding he had given a verball order, not only to me, but to the reſt of the Officers in his regiment, that in caſe any of Capt. <hi>Barringtons</hi> men were not free to go for that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, that we ſhould entertaine and lift them, in the roome of our men that were free. Whereupon eighteen of his men came to me, well mounted and well armed; and I had no ſooner entertain'd them, but the Col. ſent me an expreſſe order not to recrute; whereupon I diſcharged them, and they all marcht up to <hi>London,</hi> and were in a ſad condition, for when they came thither, they went to the Col. but could not prevaile with him to be enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained under my command, and ſo were fruſtrate of all imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and continued ſo long (notwithſtanding they had often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times petitioned the Col. and divers friends had ſolicited in their behalfe) till they had ſpent their horſes and all that they could make ſhift for; yet afterwards, (upon my Engagement of laying down my Commiſſion, as you ſhall ſee by and by, he ſent them down to me afoot, to be liſted again, as may appear by divers letters under his own hand, which was a pure peece of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, which I ſhall refer to the Reader to judge. But of this by the way.</p>
            <p>Now it came to paſſe, that I (finding the Collonels deſigne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, partly through his malice towards me, and partly ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up his own <hi>intereſt</hi>) <hi>knew that offence may be taken, though not given: but wo to him by whome offences come,</hi> and I know that wrath is cruel, anger is outrageous, <hi>and that it is a hard matter to ſtand before envie.</hi> Therefore I took my journy to <hi>London,</hi> to ſee how the caſe ſtood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt my Col. and I, but before I ſpake with him, I met with our <hi>Major,</hi> who told me that the Colonel did proſecute his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer deſigne againſt me, with all the force and ſtrength he had, and no perſwading him to the contrary, and that he told him that he had an order from the Generall to disband my whole troope, to disband me. Whereupon (having ſome farther diſcourſe with the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117922:7"/>
               <hi>Major</hi> and Capt. <hi>Neale,</hi> touching this matter, we all three concluded together, to meet at the Col. houſe, the next morning, to know what his reſolution was concerning me; but when we came, the Col. was upon exceeding high tearmes, in a rayling condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt me, and <hi>ripping up the old ſores</hi> (of his own making) by thoſe <hi>poyſonous arrowes ſhot againſt</hi> me: but I earneſtly deſired him that <hi>I might have</hi> the benefit <hi>and priviledge of a Counſel at warre;</hi> knowing that it would have bin the onely way (if I might obtain it) to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get a right underſtanding betwixt us, and the onely way to free me from ſuch aſperſions, which will not be removed, till truth be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted: but if ſo be I have either ſaid or done any thing worthy of puniſhment, (as I told him) I would aske no favour at any mans hands, but willingly ſubmit to the cenſure of the Court, either to ſtand or fall by it; and in caſe I were found guilty, I ſhould wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly ſuffer, according to my demerits. Then the <hi>Major,</hi> and Capt. <hi>Neale</hi> both, did earneſtly deſire (in my behalfe) that a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of warre might be had, whereupon the Col. (in a ſurious rage) burſt forth againſt Capt. <hi>Neale</hi> in bitter language, and told him that he was as bad as I, his turne was next, and that he might truſt to it, for he had a charge againſt him as well as againſt me, and put his hand in his pocket, pretending to produce both our charges; but did not, and truly for my part I do beleeve, that if he had drawn any charge againſt either of us, he was aſhamed to ſhew it, knowing that his own conſcience would accuſe him that he had nothing againſt either of us, that would hold water at a Counſel at warre, unleſſe he could get ſome knights of the poſt, to ſwear for him: and that I ſhall appeale to the reader to judge in that he would not admit of a Counſel at warre. And you may eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly render a reaſon, for it was becauſe he had lay'd ſuch <hi>ignominious and ſcandalous reproaches upon us that he was never able to prove one title of it.</hi> Yet notwithſtanding, he did continually ſpread abroad our names in all places where ere he came, both in City and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and eſpecially my name, he made ring throughout the whole Army, both to the Generall and Officers, as if I had bin the vileſt Creature under the Sun, inſomuch (as I conceived and was part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confident) that he had ſo far prevailed with the Generall to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band the whole troope, to disband me, according to what he had affirmed to us; and truly for my part, I tooke it to be truth what
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117922:8"/>he had ſaid, and whether the Generall were abuſed in it I know not, but for my own particular, <hi>I</hi> did not care what could be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved againſt me, for <hi>I</hi> had neither ſaid nor don any thing that <hi>I</hi> was aſhamed of, but rather then my whole Troope ſhould ſuffer for my ſake, <hi>I would lay down my Commiſſion,</hi> whereupon the Colonell preſently cloſed with me, and told me, that if I would engage to lay down my Commiſſion, he would ſpeak to the Generall that <hi>I</hi> might muſter two or three muſters, and continue my Command ſo long, that I might have my accompts ſtated, and ſetle my bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, for, ſaid he, <hi>I</hi> conceive, you will go into <hi>Ireland</hi> to your bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Col. <hi>Abbot,</hi> and I think it will be your beſt courſe you can take. Truly for my part (ſaid <hi>I</hi>) I know not how the Lord will diſpoſe of me, but you know that <hi>I</hi> was willing to go with my whole troop for that ſervice, when <hi>I</hi> was by you appointed to go, when Capt. <hi>Barrington</hi> went (all though you never intended it) therefore (<hi>I</hi> conceive) <hi>I</hi> have the more wrong, to have my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand wholly taken from me. Yet notwithſtanding, <hi>I</hi> will lay down my Commiſſion, upon thoſe tearmes, and <hi>I</hi> did engage, and ſo we parted; and I proteſt <hi>I</hi> really intended to perform my engagement, and ſo the next day <hi>I</hi> went to my troope: but for half an hour ſpace, or thereabouts, I was not without ſome ſmall trouble in my ſpirits, to think that ſuch arbitrarineſſe ſhould be exerciſed amongſt us, who had ſo zealouſly, fought againſt it in others, but my trouble was quickly over, and ſuddainly turned in to <hi>rejoycings with unſpeakable joy and comfort;</hi> in that I knew that it was the will and pleaſure of God it ſhould be ſo. And withall I had ſuch a kind of expreſſion of mirth within me, that I took my pen and inck, and wrote my caſe, (by way of indictment) as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <q>The accuſation, indictment, araignment, conviction, and ſentence, againſt, Captain Francis Freeman without a Court.</q>
            <p>Captain <hi>Freeman,</hi> thou art accuſed and indicted by the name of Captain <hi>Francis Freemen,</hi> for that thou haſt felloniouſly denyed the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and made God the <hi>Author of ſin.</hi> Thou haſt ſaid thou art <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and thou haſt countenanced <hi>blaſphemy;</hi> all which is againſt our <hi>Soveraign Lords</hi> the <hi>people,</hi> if we could but prove it. Therefore what canſt thou ſay for thy ſelf? art thou guilty; or not guilty? not guilty, by whom wilt thou be tried? <hi>I'le be tried by a generall Counſell
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117922:8"/>at Warre;</hi> no; thou canſt not, thou muſt be tryed by Colonel <hi>Okey,</hi> how? <hi>muſt I be tryed by Col. Okey?</hi> why, <hi>he hath condemned me already;</hi> what though he hath? thou canſt not be admitted to any other Tryall, Therefore ſtand up and heare thy Sentence.</p>
            <p>Thy Troop ſhall be disbanded for thy ſake, for that thou holdeſt dangerous? Tenets; how? ſhall my Troop be disbanded for my ſake? <hi>ſhall ſeventy men ſuffer for one?</hi> if I have either ſaid or done any thing worthy of puniſhment; <hi>then let me ſuffer according to my demerits.</hi> Well, tis the Generals pleaſure to disband thy whole Troop, to disband thee: nay, rather then let my whole Troop ſuffer I will lay down my commiſſion. If thou wilt engage to lay down thy commiſſion; I will ſpeak to the Generall to ſave thy Troop. And thus I have ſtated my caſe truly, by way of Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Now when I came down to my Troop, I told them what was done, who were exceedingly troubled at it, when they heard it; and did earneſtly deſire me to give way to them, to petition the Generall in my behalfe, that I might have a Councel at Warre: but I adviſed them not to doe it, and for this reaſon which I gave them, that they might ſuffer as deeply as Cap. <hi>Barringtons</hi> men did, which the Colonel had not cared a ſtraw, ſo that he might have had his will. And withall I told them, that I had engaged to lay down my commiſſion rather then they ſhould ſuffer, which cauſed no ſmall trouble of mind to them, being very loath to part from me; but you ſhall ſee how it came to paſſe upon my engagement of laying down my commiſſion: the Colonel ſent down Capt. <hi>Barringtons</hi> men to me, with an order to be liſted, and to pay them but half pay, &amp; reſerve the reſt to buy them horſes, which I did, and truly <hi>for my part</hi> I received them into the liſt as a recrute for him that ſhould <hi>ſucceed</hi> me. And afterwards I went to <hi>London,</hi> to have my accompts ſtated, and to ſettle my buſineſſe, but whileſt I was at <hi>London,</hi> it ſo fell out that my Troop concluded together, to peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Generall in my behalf. And I Profeſſe ingenuouſly, I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of it till that very day that it was exhibited, which peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was granted, and I was taken off from my former engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, being it was the Generals pleaſure to grant me a fair hearing, in caſe my accuſers did proſecute the buſineſſe, in the mean time I ſhould continue my command, which I have done
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117922:9"/>upon that account, but ſince my command hath bin taken from me neer the borders of <hi>Scotland;</hi> and without a Counſell at warre. But I ſhall omit that till it come to its proper place; and ſhall proceed where I left.</p>
            <p>Now the next time the Colonell and I met together, was at <hi>Bedford,</hi> where he challenged me upon my engagement: and told me <hi>that every boneſt man would be as good as his word:</hi> my anſwer was, that the caſe was now altered, and my engagement made void in regard the Generall had granted me a fair tryall, which (I concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) was not unknown to him, although he would not take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it, whereupon he burſt forth in his old wonted paſſion; and told me, that I <hi>was abaſe fellow, a diſhoneſt man, and he had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have a drunkard or a whore-maſter in his regiment then ſuch a one as</hi> I was; with ſuch like expreſſions, but I ſeeing him in ſuch a paſſion (being unwilling to multiply words) I told him; that I ſhould be very ready and willing at any time, to anſwer for any thing, that he or any one elſe could lay to my charge, and would aske no favour at their hands, and ſo I parted from him and left him in a rayling condition againſt me, and told the Companie that were with him (as I underſtood afterwards) that I never preſt him to have a Counſel at warre, till ſuch time, his witneſſes were gone into Irelend; pretending that ſome of my Souldiers, (who went for that ſervice) were his witneſſes, when as his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience could witneſſe againſt him, and my innocency clear me, and <hi>I</hi> dare be bold to ſay, that there was not a ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier that went but loved me ſo well, that he was as ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of my good as of his own: but howſoever, this was a notable plea of his, to make people beleeve ſtrange things of me, as if I had bin as baſe as he reported me to be, and all to make his owne matter good.</p>
            <p>Now the next newes I heard, was an order from the Major to recrute my Troope, and to raiſe them up to a hundred, beſides Officers, which I endeavoured to doe; and in the mean time, the Col. had an order to raiſe two new Troopes, in the room of thoſe two that went for the ſervice of Ireland, and his own Troop and the Majors to be made Troops of horſe: where you ſhall ſee, that his intereſtwas partly ſatisfied; yet notwithſtanding, he did not leave his deſigne ſo naked and without hopes, but he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117922:9"/>would fullfill his own will, and (for the accompliſhment thereof, you ſhall ſee how he hath given the <hi>ſelf-denying ordinance a totall rout</hi> that it cannot be able to <hi>rally again,</hi> for he got a Commiſſion, for his brother to be Captain to one Troop, his Son-in-law, to be Capt. of the other, and his brother in law to be his Lie ut. but as for his Son-in-law, he is a meer ſtranger to me, but I have heard a very good report of him, that he is a deſerving man, and truly (for my part) I know nothing to the contrary, out for the other two, I ſhall appeale to all that know them, whether or no they are fit for any ſuch imployment, unleſſe it be to receive the States money (if they can tell how to tell it) but howſoever here you may ſee a Rout, a Rout, a Rout, a totall Rout. Therefore gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, look about ye, have a care, how you make any more ſuch ſelf-denying ordinances, for God will not be mocked. But no more of this, I ſhall now proceed to the next.</p>
            <p>The next order I received, was to ſend ten of my Troop, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the raiſing of theſe two new Troopes, which was done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my order, and the like number or more was ſent out of each Troop, inſomuch that our Troopes that marcht into Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land were much weakened, and thoſe left behind, we having or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to march with all ſpeed into the North. Now the firſt randeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouz we had together (except the Colonels own Troop) was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond <hi>Swarſon-Bridge,</hi> over the river Trent, where we received or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for our ſeverall Troopes to quarter in <hi>Darbiſhire,</hi> till far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther orders, and my quarters were at a place called <hi>Morley,</hi> three miles from <hi>Darby</hi> Town; where we continued eight daies, and then according to order, we removed to a place called <hi>Tibſelfe,</hi> and quartered there till my Colonel came to <hi>Darby,</hi> who ſent for me thither to ſpeak with me, in the mean time, our Major took occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to talk with him, concerning me, and told him, that (if he could with patience hear me) he did beleeve that I would give him very good ſatisfaction in all things (eſpecially if a right un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding might be had between us) and aboured much with him, to diſcourſe with me, in a milde way; laying aſide all anger and bitterneſſe of ſpirit; which was granted by him, and he did proteſt (as the Major told me) that he had no malice, nor preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice againſt me, but ſeemed to him, to be much inclinable to a milde diſcourſe; ſo when we came together, we had a ſhort re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117922:10"/>of ſome of the old points (which <hi>were</hi> miſapprehended before) and truly for my part, I thought before we parted, he had bin fully ſatisfied, and his wrath appeaſed, for we parted upon very fair termes; and the Major did much rejoyce at it, who afterwards told the reſt of the Officers, that he did beleeve, that the buſineſſe was quite over between my Colonel and I, and that we would be very good friends for future: which cauſed them to rejoyce like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and were exceeding glad to hear of it.</p>
            <p>But now you ſhall ſee, that malice can never ly long hid, but it muſt of neceſſity burſt forth, notwithſtanding his fair outſide, and his proreſtations to the Major, that he bore no malice towards me; yet he had the very <hi>gall of bitterneſſe in his brest</hi> (as may appear) for, about three-dayes after, we had a randeſvouz, and a Muſter at <hi>Winfield</hi> manner, and we received fourteen daies pay, but till af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Muſter, there was no ſeeming prejudice againſt me: but whilſt I was receiving my money of the Major, in the Mannor-houſe, the Colonel went to my Troop, and laboured with them what poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly he could, to ſet them, againſt me. He told them, that I was a dangerous fellow, and he would place an honeſt man in my room, to command them; and flattered with them exceedingly: but my Troop anſwered him plainly, that they deſired no other Captain; they had long time had experience of me, &amp; that I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies proved an honeſt man to them. Now after I had received the money; the Major and I came up into the field (not thinking of any deſign againſt me) the Golonel called for all his Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on-officers to come to him at the head of my troop, and there made a ſpeech to them; declaring againſt me, what a dangerous man I was, one that held dangerous tenets and not fit to be in the Army; and that I and ſuch others went the occaſion of theſe warres: therefore I ſhould march no longer with them, he would give me a diſcharge there at the head of my troop, and commanded my Lieut to take charge of them, and commanded the Major likewiſe to ſend no more orders to me, but to my Lieut. but when he had thus uttered his minde, I told him, that we had fought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt arbitrarineſſe to good purpoſe, if mens wils muſt be laws; but for my part I would take no diſcharge at his hands, I had my Commiſſion from the ſame Generall as he had his; nevertheleſſe I ſhould be obedient to all juſt commands, as I alwaies had bin,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117922:10"/>but ſeeing the Generall had granted me a hearing at a Counſel at warre, I would either ſtand or fall by it: then the Colonel (in a furious rage) did proteſt, that if I marcht any more at the head of the troop, he would commit me to the Marſhal: my anſwer was, that if he did, then I was confident I ſhould have a tryall at a Counſell at warre. And ſo the Colonel and I parted, and he and ſome of his officers went to dinner with the Muſter-maſter, as they had provided ſomething for him to eat, and I marcht with my troop towards my quarters, and when I found a convenient place I drew them up, and ſpake ſomething to them, which was to this effect: That whereas there had been a great difference a long time between my Col. and I, as he pretended, for matter of judgement, although it doth evidently appear, that it was principally to ſet up his own intereſt, &amp; in proſecution thereof, he hath laboured to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der me as odious as may be poſſibly, not only to you even now, but unto all men where ere he comes, and endeavours to aſperſe me and caſt an <hi>odium</hi> upon me, to bring not only you, but all men elſe into hatred and deteſtation, not only againſt my perſon, but my actions alſo, notwithſtanding you have had ſufficient experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of my dealings towards you, and my faithfulneſſe towards all men, touching my military imployment: and I have had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient experience of your love alwayes towards me (but more eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially of late) in that you did (unknown to me) petition the Generall in my behalfe; therefore if there be any amongſt you (that my Colonel hath wrought upon (by his aſperſing of me) that have any hard thoughts againſt me; I deſire that you would ſpeak, that I may give you ſatis faction in all things, and for the future, I ſhall deſire that you would continue your obedience to my command as formerly: but if ſo be my carriage hath bin ſuch towards you, as that you deſire to have another Captain in my place, I ſhall reſt my ſelf contented, and march no farther; Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they cried unanimouſly with one conſent; <hi>no other Captain, no other Captain, we have alwaies found you faithful to us, and therefore we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire no other Captain; we will be obedient to your commands in all things; we will do whatſoever you will have as to do; and as we have petitioned the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral in your behalfe; ſo we ſhall ſtill own the petition.</hi> For which I gave them many thanks, and ſo marcht towards our quarters; but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our march, one of my ſouldiers came up to me, (as he ſaid) to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117922:11"/>tell me a pretty ſtory, and uſed this very expreſſion, that it was a true ſtory. What's that? (ſaid I) then he began to tell me, that <hi>be had a young Cookow at his quarters, and a little hedge-ſparrow fed him, but fed him ſo long till the Cookow eat off her head. Captain, ſaid he, you may pick out the Engliſh of this.</hi> With that all the Troop that heard it; burſt out in a laughter, importing thus much, that I had hatcht up a <hi>Cockatrice</hi> in my own boſome, and that my Cornet was the <hi>Cookow</hi> and I the <hi>ſparrow,</hi> having rail'd <hi>him</hi> up from a poondragoon at eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen pence <hi>per diem,</hi> being my fellow Townſ-man formerly, to be my Cornea at five ſhillings <hi>per diem,</hi> yet ſuch was his requital with ingratitude, that he was the only man, that firſt began this broil between my Colonel and I, and ſince he hath bin Cornet he hath let fall theſe or the like expreſſions among my Souldiers, that he ſhould riſe no higher in preferment, unleſſe he could leap over my Leiut. head. But what he gap'd after, I ſhall leave it for you to judge, and ſo proceed to the next.</p>
            <p>The next Randeſvouz we had, was at <hi>Whaly-bridge,</hi> where my Col. gave me another fierce charge at the head of his Regiment. He told me that I was a baſe ſcandalous fellow, and I had ſung bau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſongs upon my march, which was a griefe to all godly Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that heard me, and he named one of the ſongs, which was this, <hi>I met with Joane of Kent</hi> &amp;c. I ſhall therefore give you a true and perfect relation both of the manner, and alſo the occaſion of my finging, that you may the better ſee upon what ſlight occaſions he would take advantage againſt me. I had a Souldier in my Troop whoſe name is <hi>Reger Daniel,</hi> who was formerly a Leiut in the States ſervice, a man whom I loved very well, inſomuch as I called him my <hi>Bucking ham,</hi> my <hi>favcurit</hi> &amp;c. Who came to my quarters one morning (whileſt I quartered at <hi>Morley</hi> near <hi>Darby</hi>) and told me that he had excellent muſick at his quarters, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited me to come that night to hear it. I asked him, what mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick it was? he told me, it was gallant muſick, but did not tell me what inſlruments they were, neither did I at preſent take any more notice of what he had ſaid, nor never thought of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitation, till after ſupper; but then (it coming into my mind, I being muſical my ſelfe, and its well known can ſing my part) I went up to his quarters, where I found them at ſupper; the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the houſe bid me welcome, and as ſoon as they had ſupt,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117922:11"/>my <hi>Buckingham</hi> (as I call'd him) roſe from the Table, and went to a preſſe-cubboard, where he took out <hi>a fife-recorder,</hi> and a <hi>Citern,</hi> and delivered the recorder to the old man, and the Citern to the young man his Son, and they played half a douzen leſſons, verywell in conſort, inſomuch, that I thought they could ſing prick-ſong, therefore I deſired to know of them, whether they could or not? they anſwered no, but they had ſome delight to play upon thoſe fooliſh inſtruments (as they call'd them) and ſo played three or four leſſons more, and lay'd them aſide. Now it came to paſſe, as I ſate by them in a chair taking a pipe of Tobacco: one <hi>Ralph Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis</hi> another Souldier of mine that quartered there, having a very good voice, ſung a tune as he walked in the room, <hi>Ralph,</hi> ſaid <hi>I,</hi> thou haſt a very good voice, and ſo hath <hi>Graves,</hi> which is an other of my Souldiers, I care not if <hi>I</hi> have you two, to quarter near me, that I may teach you to ſing your ſong. Capt. ſaid my <hi>Bucking-ham,</hi> will you not teach me? why, thou haſt no good voice, ſaid I, yea, but I have a good voice, and I do not think, but I ſhall learn to ſing my part as ſoon as either of them. Doſt thou think thou canſt? ſaid I, that ſhall be tryed, and ſo began to ſing this old ſong, <hi>New oystors</hi> &amp;c. And after I had ſung it once or twice over, I ſet them in their parts, and ſhewed them their time, and ſtrook time for them with my hand, and found them very tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable, for after twice or thrice ſinging over, they ſung their parts and kept their time every well, inſomuch, as I conceived the two men of the houſe who played on the muſick before, were much taken with it, and liked our muſick very well. Then I ſung ſix or ſeven ſongs and catches by my ſelf, whereof one of them was this that my Col. hath laid to my charge; I met with <hi>Joan</hi> of Kent &amp;c. And this was another. There dwels a pretty Maid, her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name is <hi>Sis</hi> &amp;c. And theſe are the two ſongs, that goe under the notion of baudy ſongs; which <hi>I</hi> ſhall appeal to all thoſe that know what they are, and what the Muſick is. And truly for my part, I ſung but meanly for the muſick ſake, not thinking any hurt at all. Neither had I indeed any evil thoughts in my heart in ſinging any of thoſe ſongs; which my conſcience can beare me witneſſe, and it is that which muſt either <hi>accuſe me,</hi> or <hi>excuſe me.</hi> But now I ſhall ſhew you, how it came to paſſe, that my Colonel-ſhould have notice given him, of my ſinging theſe old ſonge.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:117922:12"/>
            <p>Now the woman of the houſe, where we had the muſick af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I was gone, ſhe told my <hi>Buckingham,</hi> that I was a merry man, yea, ſaid he, and I think he hath as much cauſe as any man I know, and withall ſpake ſomething concerning my enjoyments, but ſhe ſaid but little more to him: but about fourteen dayes after, ſhe went to <hi>Darby-market,</hi> and having a brother that was a ſhop-keeper there; ſhe ſpake ſomething to him concerning my mirth, and that I had ſung a great many merry ſongs at her houſe. Now you ſhall ſee how her brother wrought notably upon this newes, having heard before, how my Colonel had painted me forth to Colonel <hi>Barton,</hi> and himſelf with colours of his own making, and with his own penſell too, though it were unknown to them, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently made Colonel <hi>Barton</hi> acquainted with what his Siſter had told him concerning theſe old ſongs which I had ſung, who ſent for the woman and took her examination touching this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and drew a very formall charge againſt me, and ſent it to my Colonel as if I had committed ſome notorious crime, and as if he himſelf had been guilty of no fault at all: I ſhall be glad if his own conſcience can acquit him from being guilty of much bloud that of late hath been ſpilt. And as for Colonel <hi>Okey,</hi> I have ſeen him and others, fling Cuſhions about the houſe, at each others heads, and this hath been well taken, and not ſo much as ſpoken of; nay, once I ſaw him ſet a drunken man (which is farre worſe then any thing he hath againſt me) upon a board, in the midle of a room, to ſee whether he could go the length of the board, and not tread beſide it; and hath made ſport with him halfe an hour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, in his drunkenneſſe, and yet ſuch things as theſe are muſt paſſe as well done in him, and he himſelf thinke well of it too; when as an old ſong for the muſick ſake, cannot paſſe from me, without a charge againſt me, and it muſt be accounted, a noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious crime in me, although there was no harm at all in it. But howſoever, this verifies the old proverb, <hi>that one man may better ſteale a horſe, then another man may look over the hedge.</hi> Beſides, I have ſeen him ſometimes merry with his Officers: and ſometimes again not an Officer durſt ſcarce ſpeake to him; and this verifies an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, that one uſed of him once in my hearing. that <hi>he is either all hony, or all</hi>—And truly for my part I have not had a good word from him, in eight moneths together; neither could I ever
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117922:12"/>ſay, or do any thing in all this time that would pleaſe him. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I thought good to write a letter unto him, to ſee whether my lines might be any way pleaſing unto him; and when I came to <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> I ſent my letter by our Major, who carefully delivered it, but I never received any anſwer at all from my Colonel, till I came to the head-quarters, at a place called <hi>Anwick,</hi> where my Colonel was got before me, and had prevailed ſo farre with the Generall, upon his own informations againſt me, as to grant him an order, to put me beſide my command without a Councell at warre, which when I heard of it, I made haſte to the head quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and came in the morning before the Generall was ſtirring, and ſo I went to Mr. <hi>Clarkes</hi> chamber, one of the Generalls Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries to ſee whether there was any ſuch order granted to my Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel againſt me; and Mr. <hi>Clarke</hi> told me there was, and ſhewed me the order. Then I deſired to know of him whether the order might not be reverſt upon moving the General for a <hi>Councell at war,</hi> that he might have a right underſtanding of the difference betvvixt us? which he told me, that he thought it might; for it was all the reaſon in the vvorld, that I ſhould have a fair hearing, and that it vvas my Lord Generall <hi>Fairfex</hi> his pleaſure upon my Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers petitioning, to grant it unto me: But whilſt vve vvere thus talking, Colonel <hi>Okey came</hi> in for the order, and ſeeing <hi>me</hi> there he fell out vvith <hi>me</hi> exceedingly, and all to be ſpattred <hi>me</hi> vvith his old vvonted language, and told <hi>me</hi> that I vvas a baſe fellovv, and that I had vvrote a baſe ſcurrelous and ſcandalous letter unto <hi>him.</hi> Sir, ſaid I, I have a Coppy of the letter, and I ſhall deſire that it <hi>may</hi> be read, that other Men <hi>may</hi> judge of it, as vvell as your ſelf, and ſo put <hi>my</hi> hand in <hi>my</hi> pocket to produce it. no, ſaid he, you need not ſhevv the coppy, here is the letter it ſelf, and ſo delivered it to Mr. <hi>Clarke,</hi> although it vvas not his intended purpoſe that it ſhould be read, as did evidently appear to us; for he had not read above three or four lines, but the Colonel fell into a bitter paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on again, and told <hi>me,</hi> that he vvould cut <hi>me</hi> over the noſe, and gave <hi>me</hi> very uncivil language, inſomuch that Mr. <hi>Clerk</hi> brake off reading the letter, by reaſon of his interrupting of <hi>him,</hi> vvhich vvas on purpoſe, that he ſhould not read it, as <hi>may</hi> be gathered, vvhereupon I deſired the Colonel that he vvould vvith patience ſuffer it to be read, vvhich if he vvould not, I told <hi>him</hi> plainly,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117922:13"/>that the coppy ſhould, which was a tying of himup, that he could not for ſhame but ſuffer it to be read, which being done <hi>Mr. Clerck</hi> toldhim that there was not a word nor ſyllable of ſcandalous lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grage againſt him in it, and that it was as fair a letter, as ever he read, counting how the caſe ſtood betwixt us; which put him to ſilence for that charge, and ſo we parted.</p>
            <p>Now when I came to the Generall, I deſired that favour of him, that I might have a faire hearing at a Counſell at warre, that the difference between my Colonel and I might be heard and determined by them, that I might no longer ly under ſuch ſcandalous imputations, and if ſo be my innocency would not cleare me; that then I might ſuffer according to my deſervings: in the mean time, (while I was thus ſpeaking) in came my Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel with divers Colonels more with him; whom I concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſome of them to be very right for the carrying on of the work, as may appear by their carriage towards me: for there was ſcarce any thing that I could ſpeak, but ſome of them took exceptions againſt it: although the Generall took none at all: for firſt my Col. charged me with my engagement of layingdown my Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; which the <hi>General</hi> deſired to know of me, whether it were true or no? my anſwer was, yea, it was true: I did engage: but my engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was madevoide by my Lord <hi>General Fairfax</hi> who granted me a fair hearing at a <hi>Counſel</hi> at warre, upon my ſouldiers petitioning in my behalfe. Then did my Col. burſt forth againſt me in very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civil language (according to his accuſtomed practiſe) his tongue being inur'd to ſuch language for eight monethsſpace together, you know it might come the more fluently from him. He told the Generall that I was a baſe unworthy fellow, and not fit to be in the Army. And having railed at me ſufficiently, and indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to diſparage me as much as might be poſſible, then I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly moved the General again and preſt exceedingly, that I might have a Counſell at warre, to ſee whether he could prove what he ſaid, or any thing thr he had or could lay to my charge, for (ſaid I) it is his pleaſure to ſpeak any thing a gainſt me, to make his own matter good, and to fulfill his own will, but if ſo be I would have a Counſell at warr, Then he muſt prove what he ſpeakes, which expreſſion of mine, was very ill takenby ſome (though not by the Generall) for there was one Colonel which did by way of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117922:13"/>acclamation, cry. Oh was there ever any officer in the Army, that ever gave ſuch language to their Colonel? as who ſhould ſay, I had given him the ly, or at leaſt, queſtioned the truth of what he had ſaid: when as for my part, <hi>I</hi> thought he had bin reſolved, never to ſpeak truth any more. Nay ſuch was the carriage of ſome of them towards me, as if ſo be Captaines were ſuch low-prized Officers, that they muſt be ſubject to bear every burden that their Coloneis ſhall lay upon them; and to be like <hi>Iſachars</hi> Aſſe, to <hi>crouch</hi> under every burden; and to bear all <hi>ſeandalous</hi> reproaches, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to them with ſilence: pardon theſe expreſſions, for <hi>I</hi> can aſſure you, <hi>I</hi> cannot help it. Neither do <hi>I</hi> blame any of you, for doing what you did againſt me, but no more of this; for this is by way of digreſſion. I ſhall now proceed weere <hi>I</hi> left.</p>
            <p>Then did my Colonel produce his charge againſt me, for ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the old ſongs before mentioned, and railed at <hi>me</hi> exceedingly in the preſence of the Generall and the reſt of the officers, and told <hi>me</hi> that I was a baſe fellow and that Captain <hi>Bliſſet</hi> knew well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough what I was, and bid <hi>me</hi> aske Captain <hi>Bliſſet</hi> what I was, as if I had not known <hi>my</hi> ſelf as well as I had known <hi>him;</hi> as for Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Bliſſet</hi> I wiſh <hi>him</hi> well for the good he hath received: I fear not any charge that can or ſhall be brought in againſt <hi>me,</hi> being, I thank God, at peace within <hi>my</hi> ſelf, and with all <hi>men.</hi> Then did the Generall aske <hi>me,</hi> what the occaſion was of <hi>my</hi> ſinging thoſe ſongs? I told <hi>him</hi> the occaſion, and gave a true relation thereof, and in the ſelf ſame manner, as before recited; and that I had not ſung any ſong at all, that I need be aſhamed of, although it were the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonels pleaſure, to put them forth under the notion of baudy ſongs, and truly I did but uſe this expreſſion (by way of affirmation of what I had declared) which expreſſion was this, as I live, it is a truth Sir, (ſaid I) but I was preſently reproved for it. Oh what an expreſſion is there? ſaid one of the Colonels: as if it had bin a very vile expreſſion, and as if God himſelf, had never uſed any ſuch expreſſion to poor finners; but howſoever, ſuch an expreſſion could not ſtand before his purity, or his own ſelf-righteouſneſſe: or I may rather ſay, his Phariſaicall hypocriſie and diſſimulation; for <hi>I</hi> am afraid, that ſome of them are apt enough to affirm lies to be truths, by worſe expreſſions, though ſmoother carried on befor, men. But what good their purity, and ſelf-righteouſneſſe, will do them at the laſt great and terrible day, I know not: but I beleeve
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117922:14"/>it will ſtand them but in little ſteed, for except your righteouſneſſe exceed the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phariſees &amp;c. But I am very loth to digreſſe. But to proceed.</p>
            <p>Now the next thing which <hi>I</hi> obſerved was, that the Colonell told the General that I either had him in print, or elſe intended to put him in <hi>print</hi> ſuddainly; why, are you aſhamed to be in print? or are you afraid of it? (ſaid I) <hi>I</hi> have not as yet; but truely for my part <hi>I</hi> think <hi>I</hi> ſhall be conſtrained to put you in print to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate my ſelfe, ſeeing <hi>I</hi> cannot have a Counſel at war. Then ſaid the Generall (if <hi>I</hi> miſtake not, neither can I afficm it to be a truth) that I might have a counſell at warre hereafter. But for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent he thought fit to part my Colonel and I, in regard of the preſent expedition, and the long continuance of the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us, then it ſeems to me, that you are minded that I ſhall leave my command, ſaid I, yea, ſaid the General, ſo I ſaw their reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, and that it was but a folly for me to preſſe him any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. I told him, though <hi>I</hi> were ſubject to many aſperſions, and that I ſhould ly under a cloud for a time, yet nevertheleſſe, I ſhould ſubmit to his pleaſure, and ſo took my leave of the Generall. But howſoever, here you may ſee my Colonels kindneſſe towards me, and that he was more kind to me then <hi>Ioah</hi> was to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riab:</hi> for <hi>Ioab</hi> ſet <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riab</hi> in the fore-front of the battell: but my Colonel inſtead of ſetting me in the fore-front of the battel, he put me quite beſide my command.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>I</hi> ſhall ſhew you another piece of the Colonels kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe towards my Lieut. After my command was taken away, my Lieut. (knowing that the Troop did properly belong unto him) went to <hi>Barwick</hi> to the Colonel to deſire him that he might have it, and uſed the beſt arguments he could to obtain it, he told him that he was the oldeſt Lieut. in the Army, and that there had bin three Captaines put in over his head, which was not unknown to him, and ſome other arguments he laid down; yet all in vain, he could not prevaile with him, but bid him hold his tongue, and be contented with that command he had: if he were not contented, he would help him to thirty pound for his commiſſion preſently, if he would lay it down, &amp; get him home: as if ſo be, Commiſſions were to be bought and ſold like horſes in Smithefild, and you know that thirty pound will buy a good horſe there. But howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117922:14"/>the Colonel bad like a good chap-man, he offered chap-man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like I promiſe ye, and preſent pay too; but it ſeems the Lieut. could not afford it at the price, therefore they could not bargain. But if ſo be they had bargained tis like the Colonel would have been no loſer by it. But peradventure the Colonel was too raſh, in offering money before he asked the price, for commonly in Smith-Feeld they do uſe to aske the price, before they offer any money, and truly for my part, I know not the reaſon why he ſhould offer ſo much money for his commiſſion; unleſſe it were to monopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize all to himſelf and his Friends who are of the ſame mold and ſtamp with him, or at leaſt can comply with him. But howſoever I ſhall leave it to the Reader to find out ſome other arguments, for the ground of theſe things, leaſt I ſhould be miſtaken, and reſt my ſelfe ſatisfied, with confidence that the time will come and is now at hand, that Colonel <hi>Okey,</hi> and all ſuch uſurping Tyrants that exerciſe ſuch arbitrarineſſe, will be willing to give three times thirty pound to ſuch officers, as will ſtand to maintain and uphold their power, if they can tell where to have them. Nay (for ought I know) it may be they will bid like faire Chapmen, and give more.</p>
            <p>But truly friends; I muſt tell you plainly, that it is not my wonted practiſe to write in ſuch a phraſe or method as this is, for it is contrary to my ſpirits ſo to do, but that itis ſutiable to the Colonels dealing towards me. Therefore I could not but do it, and the rather to vindicate my ſelfe, in ſuch a kind of dialect; for peradventure it may the better work upon his ſpirits; knowing that my own conſcience will not ſuffer me to write any untruths, although we know that ſuch as will proſecute their deſignes, by falſe and ſcandalous accuſations, are very apt to deny truths. But ſuppoſe that Colonel. <hi>Okey</hi> ſhould queſtion any of theſe truths herein contained, ſo farre as it concerns himſelf, then I know his own conſcience will accuſe him, and bear witneſſe againſt him, and be ready to fly in the very face of him for it; and this very book of mine will prove to be a devil to torment him, as bad as ſeven devils. But ſuppoſe he ſhould think to carry it off with a high hand (as he knows how to do it pretty well) and call me knave for my labour, as once he call'd Captain <hi>Mercer,</hi> and told him he was troubled with a company of knaves to his Officers.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117922:15"/>nay, ſuppoſe he ſhould all to be ſpatter me with ſuch uncivil lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage behind my back, according to his wonted practiſe before my face, and ſay that theſe are not truths which I have written, and that I have done him wrong; then I ſhall appeal to thoſe ſix Troops of his own Regiment, which are with him in <hi>Scotland,</hi> both Officers and Souldiers, who for the generality of them, know them to be truths. And this will prove to be a tormenter indeed, when there ſhall be ſo many witneſſes againſt him; beſides his own conſcience is as a thouſand witneſſes more.</p>
            <p>But me thinks, I hear him raile at me exceedingly, and at my book, and lay this poor book to my charge, for a baſe ſcurrelous and ſcandalous book, as he did my letter which I ſent to him at <hi>Lancaſter.</hi> Then I ſhall appeal to the letter it ſelfe, whereof I ſhall give you a true Coppy, which is as followeth; and leave it to you to judge.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Am at preſent under a cloud of aſperſions (though undeſervedly) by reaſon of ſome miſapprehenſions, or miſunderſtandings one of another, which occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions ſome diſtemper and trouble of mind to ſome: Yet I praiſe my God, there is no man can take away my comforts from me; for I behold the Lord indeed in this appearance, and ſee him in all other his various workings; what though I am defamed in my good name? it is the Fathers pleaſure it ſhould be ſo. What though I ly under a cloud for a time in regard of an outward appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance before men? Yet when the day-ſtarre ſhall ariſe in your beart, and that truth may be manifeſted, it will cauſe you to have ſome trouble of mind, and auxiity of ſpirit, for theſe my ſufferings. Your conſcience will tell you, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you proſecute this deſigne againſt me, for ſome by-ſiniſter-ends, as to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance ſelfe-intereſt, or out of ſure zeal; truly for my parts in doth not appear to me, that your do it our of pure zeale, it ſavours to little of a ſpirit rightly qualified, but if it be out of pure zeal, truly ſuch zeale muſt be burnt up, or at leaſt cleanſed and purified from the droſſe, for there is abundance of mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. You ſay that I, and ſuch others, are the occaſion of theſe warres. Truly for my Part it doth appear to me, that it ariſes from pride, and ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loftyneſſe, and not from an humble and contrite heart; for ambition carries a great ſtroake, and from whence come warres? is it not from your luſts? you lay, that every honeſt man will be as good as his word, and charge me
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117922:15"/>for not making good my engagement, which was to lay down my commiſſion. And truly for my part, I really intended it, and was againſt my Souldiers petition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Generall, knowing of the ſuffering of Captain Barringtons men, who lay in <hi>London,</hi> till they had ſpent their horſes, and all that they could make ſhift for, before they could have any imployment. Beſides you know, that you would not affoard me a hearing at a Councel in Warre: leſſe then which could not be granted to the meaneſt Souldier in the Armie. But ſince the caſe is altered (as I told you) for above two moneths afire, my Souldiers much mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing at your hard dealings towards me, that you would not grant me a tryall, (unknown to me) did petition the Generall to that purpoſe, which petition was granted, and I tooke is to be a great favour, conſidering what informations you hed given in againſt me, to render me as odious, as might be poſſible. Now I ſhall appeale to your own canſcience, whether or no, you have made good all your former engagements, notwithſtanding they were of leſſe concernment, then this is to me; then look upon the equitableneſſe of the cauſe, and ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no, a deprivation of my liberty may not ſtand in competition, according to your former engagement, with my non prformance of my promiſe. Beſides, if I ſhould be put off upon theſe tearmes, without a Councel at Warre; it may breed ſome diſtractions amongſt the Officers in the Army, which is not my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire; knowing that there is no preſident for any ſuch thing, nor was there ever ſuch arbitrarineſſe exerciſed amongſt them. And it will be abundance of diſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to my friends (who are lovers of truth) in regard I ſhall still ly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a cloud of aſperſions, and not capable of any future imployment. New if ſo be there be that righteous law within you, to do as you would be done by: Then I conceive you cannot exerciſe any ſuch power. Beſides we all engaged againſt all arbitrary-power, and will you ſet it up in your ſelfe? ſurely this muſt be deſtroyed in you, or elſe you will be deſtroyed in it. For what art thou O Man that findeſt fault with another man, and thou thy ſelfe doeſt the ſame thing? You ſay that I am a heathen. Truly for my part <hi>I</hi> thinke it better to be amongſt beath ens, then amongſt ſuch profeſſors; ſuch as have a form of godlineſſe, but deny the power thereof. You pretend abundance of zeal of religion, and to religious men; but I ſee but little juſtice towards me. The Lord ſpeakes by the mouth of the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah, chapter 5. verſe 1. Runne ye to and fro, into the ſtreets of Jeruſalem, and ſee now, and know, and ſeek in the broad places therof, if ye can ſind a mar, if there by any that executeth judgement, that ſeeketh the truth; and he will pardon the City.</hi> And though they ſay, the Lord liveth, yet they ſwear falſly: <hi>verſe 2. now if ſo be juſtice be not to be found in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:117922:16"/>ſuch a great City, then where ſhal we find it but at the fountain?</hi> You yet charge me with error, and hereſie, truly for my part, I take hereſie to be a work of the fleſh, and he that is without ſin, and free from the workes of the fleſh, let him caſt the firſt ſtone; but the fruit of the ſpirit, it love, joy, peace, long-ſuffering gentleneſſe, goodneſſe, faith, meekneſſe, temperance &amp;c. And the Apoſtle laies down this as a rule too; that if a man be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken in a fault, ye which are ſpiritual, reſtore ſuch a one in the ſpirit of meekneſſe, and bear one another burdens, and ſo fulfill the Law of Chriſt. Suppoſe <hi>I</hi> had bin overtaken in a fault, which my conſcience can plead my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency and integrity, yet will you ſtill perſiſt and go on in violence against me without due examination? I ſhall deſire that you would with patience heare me what I can ſay for my ſelf, and not raſhly judge and condemn me without a cauſe; but I know you cannot help it, you are ſo overſwayed with paſſion, You ſee how large a letter I have written unto you with mine own hand; but I am a fraid of you, leſt <hi>I</hi> have beſtowed upon you labour in vain. <hi>I</hi> write in the Apoſtles own language. Sir, <hi>I</hi> beſeech you be as <hi>I</hi> am, for I am as you are, you have not injured me at all. And thus to a void prolixity; <hi>I</hi> ſhall ceaſe to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you any farther at this time, and ſhall remain.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your faithful ſervant in all duties of Command FRANCIS FREEMAN.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>And now friends, you that have read this letter I ſhall deſire that you would once more (if you are not ſatisfied) look it over, with a more attentive eye, and without any prejudicat thoughts on either ſide, and ſo go give your judgement impartially, and if ſo be you find any ſuch baſe, ſcurrelous and ſcandalous language in it (according to the matter of charge laid againſt me, then I ſhall deſire you to caſt a blur, not only upon it, but upon me, and throw dirt in my face with as much diſdain and diſgrace, as may be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible. And truly for my part, I preſume (if I might have had a Counſel at warre) you would have found, all the reſt of his charge againſt me, to be as <hi>frivelous</hi> as this: but if ſo be I may have a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell at warre hereafter (as I make no doubt but I ſhall) when once this great buſineſſe in <hi>Scotland</hi> is over: then I beleeve I ſhall make
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117922:16"/>him aſhamed of what he hath done againſt me, not that I can do any thing by way of revenge, it is againſt my ſpirit ſo to do; but by way of vindication; for I know he could not help it, he was acted by a greater power then his own, neither can I blame him for it, for he did as he ſhould do, but if ſo be I might have the greatreſt Command as might be under Colonel <hi>Okey,</hi> I profeſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniouſly, I could not take it, if I might gain 1000 pound by it: as to have my ſpirits bound up, and tyed faſt to the wils of men, and to be in bondage and ſlavery, through the beggerly rudiments of the world, by the doctrines and tradition of men, and all by an arbitrary power exerciſed over us; but if ſo be, I may be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to this Common-wealth, in any thing I can do, I ſhall be (as formerly I have bin) ready &amp; willing to do it to the uttermoſt of my power: either in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> or <hi>Ireland.</hi> But I ſhall ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chuſe to traile a pike under the great Turke, then to have any command under Colonel <hi>Okey.</hi> And Now I ſhall ſhew you one notable cunning ſlight more, that he uſed againſt me, about this time twelvemoneth: to ſet up his own intereſt, he (having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived an order to ſend two troops of his Regiment, for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of <hi>Ireland</hi>) did appoint my troop to be one: ſuppoſing, that I had not bin free for that ſervice, and ſo to diſband me upon that account; for he never intended that I ſhould go. Now for my part I was very free for that ſervice, and did expreſſe my willingneſſe to go: and my ſouldiers likewiſe did (as it were) unanimouſly with one conſent expreſſe their willingneſſe to go with me, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he was croſt in his deſigne, and then he told me, that we ſhould not go, and ever ſince he hath bin plotting, and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving all the miſchief that might be poſſible againſt me; and truly for my part, I conceived, that we were at that time, in a capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city fitteſt to go for that ſervice of any troop in his Regiment, and for theſe reaſons following <hi>viz.</hi> that we owed nothing in our quarters, when other troops owed conſiderable ſums, we were beſt mounted of any troop, well clad in good apparel, and all accou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traments belonging to ſouldiers; ſtout, gallant men, and ſuch as I dare be bold to ſay, that the Colonel never had a gallanter troop in his Regiment, ſince he was Colonel; and for my own particular part (it is well known) I have faithfully ſerved the State, ever fince the beginning of theſe troubles; and ſo I praiſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117922:17"/>my God, there is no man can challenge me for the worth of a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that ever I plundered any man, but alwaies laboured for the preſervation of the Country where ever I came. And as for my military imployment, touching my charge (before or ſince I came to this Regiment) no man can any way diſparrage me, but that I have behaved my ſelfe, in all ſervices of command like a Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; and my deportment, and carriage hath bin ſuch towards all men, as might become an honeſt man; and that no man, I dare be bold to ſpeak to the whole world, can have any juſt cauſe againſt me.</p>
            <p>And as it hath bin heretofore the ſence of the whole <hi>Army,</hi> that no <hi>man</hi> ſhould ſuffer for his opinion; ſo (I conceive) I have not in the leaſt tittle made a breach of any law, neither is there any ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle againſt me, in the whole book of articles at warre, <hi>and where there is no law, there is no tranſgreſſion.</hi> But howſoever, here you may ſee an obſolute diſcovery of my adverſaries malice towards me; and how they have made good the former part of this Epiſtle viz. that every form is a perſecuter. &amp;c. and how they have ſet up their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, by cloathing themſelves with the fig-leaves of their own righteouſneſſe, which is the righteouſneſſe of the Law; not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their freedom by Chriſt: <hi>but are in bondage to the elements of the world.</hi> Gal. 4.3. <hi>Ye obſerve daies, and moneths, and times, and years,</hi> verſe 10. <hi>but</hi> I <hi>am afraid of you, leaſt</hi> I <hi>have beſtowed upon you labour in vain. Brethren</hi> I <hi>beſeech you, be as</hi> I <hi>am, for</hi> I <hi>am as ye are, ye have not injured me at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But ſome will ſay, that the Apoſtle</hi> Paul <hi>(which you ſpeak of) had bin a perſecuter himſelf, and was he under forms?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer yea, he was under ſeverall formes, or miniſtrations but was very zealous concerning the law, and yet he thought he did God good ſervice in perſecuting the Church of Chriſt. But this was before his converſion; for afterwards, we read that he was rapt up into the third heaven, then doubtleſſe he was above all formes, types, and ſhadowes, and was ſvvallowed up in the very ſubſtance it ſelf; which formerly he had ſeen but darkly ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed forth to him by the lavv. It is even ſo vvith theſe men, vvho are under formes, and legal diſpenſations, who are my accuſers: only this difference (what ever their pretences are) what <hi>Paul</hi> did, was out of pure zeal touching the Law; wherein it is ſaid, <hi>he
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:117922:17"/>thought be walked blameleſſe:</hi> but theſe men are altogether for their own ends; and unleſſe they ſhould come to be where <hi>Paul</hi> was, viz. rapt up into the third heaven; they will go on ſtill in their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution. For 'tis impoſſible to ſee what <hi>Paul</hi> did ſee, unleſſe they could be where <hi>Paul</hi> was.</p>
            <p>And now truly friends, as I have wrote this Epiſtle to all ſorts of men (which is by way of vindication) ſo I ſhall deſire you to read this enſuing treatiſe with out any prejudicate opinions, where you ſhall in like manner find ſome other accuſations againſt me, thought unjuſtly; which will alſo diſcover abundance of folly, and weakeneſſe of thoſe my accuſers. And you may alſo find a parcel of good councel, if you can take it, communicated to all ſorts of men, both high and low, rich and poor.</p>
            <p>And although, I know, it will be accounted a ſawcy part for me to give councell or advice to Rulers, and ſuch as are in authority over us, great potentates, and mighty men of the World; yet I could not but doe it, and the rather becauſe I wiſh a happy peace to this poor bleeding Nation, and that the ſore-ſick maladies thereof might be cured. And not only to this Nation, but to all the Nations of the earth. I knovv it is God alone, that can heal the Nations, and bring all earthly povvers in ſubjection to his will. Good Councel may be offered, though not received, and if it be not received, 'tis becauſe they cannot take it. And this I know too, that the Lord ſometimes ſtirres up poor vveak and deſpiſed inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to give councel and adviſe to Princes and great vviſe men of the World, both Magiſterial and Military to confound the wiſdome of the wiſe, yea and things that are not, to bring to nought things that are, that no fleſh ſhould glory in his preſence. And as my Epiſtle is directed to all ſorts of men; ſo is my councel, and my deſire is to be inſtrumental, if the Lord ſo pleaſe, to work upon your ſpirits, for the healing of the <hi>Nations,</hi> which is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal aim and end of him, who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine, and the Nations Servant <hi>Francis Freeman.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:117922:18"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Od (who at ſundry times paſt, and in divers man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners) ſpeak unto the ſons of men in parables, and dark ſaying, and now in theſe latter times, he hath more manifeſtly declared himſelf by his Sonne, and by the holy Ghoſt the comforter; who wil both lead and guide us into the way of <hi>all truth:</hi> and although the Lord hath bin pleaſed to unveile himſelf, and to make glorious diſcoveries of himſelf unto ſome, in ſhewing forth the glorious beauty and brightneſſe of his raies, in the light and diſpenſation of the Goſpel, by his providence, yet (notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) we find by experience, that there are many precious, excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and moſt glorious truths obſcured, clouded, and overſpread with Antichriſtian darkneſſe, by reaſon of an Antichriſtian power of darkneſſe raigning amongſt us, who labouring to divert that current, or ſtream (iſſuing, or flowing from that moſt ſweet and precious fountain of truth, the Lord Ieſus) out of its proper chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, into a filthy, loathſome, durty, muddy channell of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane inventions and traditions: crying down glorious truths, to be errors, hereſies and blaſphemies, as if there were no truths declared, but ſuch as they apprehend to be ſo; when as there is an incapacity of apprehending it be carnal wiſdome: Therefore it muſt needs paſſe under that notion, eſpecially, by ſuch, who are accounted Miniſters of the Goſpel, and are no leſſe then deceivers, and being deceived, having a form of Godlyneſſe, but denying the power thereof, yet notwithſtanding, they are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held by the power of earthly Magiſtrates, who carry on their work in perſecuting the Saints and Servants of God, (as much as in them lies) But how ſoever there is a reſtraining power, and that is Gods power; which over-tops all earthly powers, when as their Mountaines ſhall be layed low, and without a manifeſtation of Gods mercy towards them, they ſhall be brought to ſhame and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of faces, for this and the like cruelties, when they ſhall cry out and there ſhall be none to help: for as the mercies of the wicked
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:117922:18"/>are cruelty and oppreſſion; ſo there are none that live godly in Chriſt Ieſus, but ſhall ſuffer perſecuſion, either by falſe accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, impriſonment, or both: which I my ſelf (being one of the leaſt and meaneſt of Gods ſervants) have my ſhare, not long ſince at the Town of <hi>Taunton</hi> in the County of <hi>Summerſet,</hi> being talſly accuſed, by one <hi>Cox,</hi> of no leſſe then blaſphemy, impriſoned by the Magiſtrates, bound over with two ſurities, to anſwer it at the aſſizes, and there indicted for blaſphemy, and the indictment pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted with as much violence as envy and malice it ſelf could im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agine, rendring me ſo odious, as not fit to live upon the earth: as if they themſelves were men of ſuch infallible judgement that there could be no truths held forth by me (being a poor weak diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſed inſtrument) but what ſhall come within the compaſſe of their appreheſions; when as the Goſpel is a hidden Miſtery. I <hi>thank thee O Father Lord of Heaven and earth, that thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe and prudent, and haſt revealed them unto babes &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord (who is the ſearcher of all hearts) can plead my inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency towards man, and mine integrity to the truth, as it is in Ieſus; who gave into me, that word of truth, by his ſpirit, which is the ſpirit of truth in the manifeſtation thereof; and ſweetly car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried me on, in the diſcovery of that truth (to the glory of his grace be it ſpoken) with that ſpirit of boldneſſe, and undauntedneſſe of ſpirit, that my Adverſary durſt not look truth in the face, to diſpute thoſe points with me, before the Magiſtrates, neither (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed) would they admit of any diſpute, but told me, that Mr. <hi>Cox</hi> had taken his oath poſſitively, that I had ſpoken blaſphemy, and his oath was for the King; they having an implicit faith, hand-o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-head, with out due examination, took his accuſation for truth, though falſe and ſcandalous; yet would not take my own recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance (notwithſtanding I was member of the Army at that time, but committed me to priſon, where, <hi>I</hi> praiſe God, my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience can plead my innocency and guiltleſſeneſſe, for what I was accuſed, inſomuch that my impriſonment and ſufferings was ſweet, comfortable and joyous unto me; knowing that ſuch ſufferings are a part of my portion, hear in this life.</p>
            <p>Now for the clearing of my ſelf from thoſe aſperſions caſt upon me; and for the vindication of thoſe truths then held forth by me, for which I was accuſed, and now ſtand Indicted, I ſhall (by
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:117922:19"/>the aſſiſtance of the Almighty) labour to undeceive the people, that they my come to a clear underſtanding of thoſe my ſufferings, that the truth may be the more manifeſted, Chriſt Jeſus exalted, and the Kingdome of Antichriſt deſtroyed, which the Lord will do one day with the breath of his mouth, and brightneſſe of his coming. And for my more orderly proceeding herein; I ſhall give you a true and perfect deſcription, both of the manner of our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and alſo the manner of their carriage towards me, and ſo leave it to the Godly-wiſe to judge. I ſhall begin with the firſt particular, touching our diſcourſe, and ſo proceed to the reſt in order as they ly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faith was the point which we inſiſted on; and this was my very expreſſion:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That he that hath faith, he is in Chriſt, and Chriſt in him; ſo that faith is Chriſt, and he is Chriſt. But this he denied. Then I asked him, whether he had faith? his anſwer was, that he did hope he had, then I told him, that he muſt have ſome ground for it, and if he had faith, then theſe ſignes ſhould follow them that beleeve, and cited that Scripture <hi>Mark</hi> 16. they ſhall caſt out devils &amp;c. And he that hath <hi>faith</hi> as a grain of Muſterd-ſeed, he ſhal be able to remove mountains. Then he asked me, whether I had faith? my anſwer was, yea, Then ſaid he, you are Chriſt, you are able to remove Mountaines; my anſwer was, yea, I was able to remove Mountaines. Then he farther replyed, and ſaid thus, if you are Chriſt you are God, you are here, you are at <hi>London,</hi> you are every where, <hi>my</hi> anſwer was, yea, though not eſſentially, as I am in this body of fleſh, but in reſpect of that ſpirituall oneneſſe, with him, and in him: and that I am here, and at <hi>London;</hi> and above <hi>London.</hi> Then we ſpake ſomething concerning the perſonality of the Deity. which point was quickly ended, for the would ſtay no longer to diſpute out thoſe points with me; but framed ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe to be gon, ſaying, that he had a great deal of buſineſſe. Then I earneſtly deſired him to ſtay, that I might make forth theſe points to him, but he would not. <hi>Then I made them clear to my friend which was with us,</hi> who told me, that Mr. <hi>Cox</hi> was not able to diſpute theſe points with me: which he conceived was the reaſon of his haſte.</p>
            <p>This diſcourſe was about twelve a clocke, and I heard no more newes of it, till about nine at night; at which time the Conſtables and other officers, came for me to goe before the Major, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:117922:19"/>
               <hi>Nicolas;</hi> which when I came thither, there was mine accuſer: and had taken his oath (as they ſaid) that I had ſpoken blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and laid this to my charge; that I ſaid I was Chriſt, I was God, and that I denyed the Trinity: My anſwer was, that he accuſed me falſly, and ſaid, that I do acknowledge three ſubſiſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in one divine eſſence, in reſpect of their ſeverall operations. Then ſaid he, you denyed the perſonality, my anſwer was, that I am not ſo low, and carnall, as to bring down a Deity, to a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonality, Then Juſtice <hi>Nicolas</hi> cited that Scripture in <hi>John: There are three which bare record in heaven, the Father, the Word, and the holy Ghoſt.</hi> But my anſwer was, that I did not read, <hi>that there were three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons did bear record in heaven.</hi> Then he farther replyed, and ſaid, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is ſaid in Scripture, to be the expreſſe Image of his Fathers perſon; to which I anſwered, that that was ſpoken touching his divinity, and withall earneſtly deſired to diſpute out theſe points with mine accuſer, that I might clear thoſe truths held forth by me; but they would not admit of any diſpute. Then my accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, by way of aggravation, told me that I ſaid that I could remove mountains. My anſwer was, that he knew not what a Mountain was. Then Juſtice <hi>Nicolas</hi> told me, that I deſpiſed the Miniſters of the Goſpel: my anſwer was, no, I loved the Miniſters of the Goſpel: but for my part I conceived my accuſer to be none, and withall, deſired to diſpute out that point with him too, to ſee whether he could make forth his calling, but that would not be granted neither. Then ſaid Juſtice <hi>Nicolas,</hi> Captain <hi>Freeman,</hi> It is a ſtrange thing that there ſhould be ſuch errors and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies abroad, and ſuch diverſities of opinions amongſt us, being brethren. To which I anſwered, that I did not take him to be a Brother, unleſſe it were according to the fleſh, in <hi>Adam.</hi> Then he told me that I muſt either find ſureties to anſwer it at the next aſſizes, or go to priſon: My anſwer was, that for the preſent, I muſt ſubmit to the power of the Magiſtrate: and ſo choſe rather to go to priſon, then to ſend for ſureties. And ſo my <hi>Mittimus</hi> was to be made, and the Clerk put his jear upon me; he asked me what my dipt name was? I reproving him for it, the Juſtice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved me. Then I told them that our Saviour Chriſt, was accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a blaſphemer: and the ſervant muſt not look to be above his Maſter; and withall told them, that they ſought what meanes
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:117922:20"/>they could to betray me; and cited that Scripture <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. Where the Sadduces went about to betray our ſaviour Chriſt, touching his reſurrection. but he told them that <hi>they erred, not knowing the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures,</hi> by this time my mittemus was made, and the Officers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to take me away; Then my accuſer, inſultingly, asked the Major, whether he had any more ſervice to command him, Mr. <hi>Major</hi> anſwered, and ſaid, that he muſt ſtay, for he muſt be bound to give evidence againſt me. Then I cited that Scripture in <hi>Hoſea</hi> 5.11. verſe. <hi>Ephraim is oppreſſed, and broken in judgement, becauſe he willingly walked after the Commandments.</hi> and withall asked him, what commandments thoſe were; but he anſwered not a word. And ſo I went to priſon, where I praiſe God, I received abundance of comfort; for divers of the Gathered Church, came to viſit me, and tendred themſelves to be my ſureties; ſo on the next day I ſent a latter to the <hi>Major.</hi> A true Coppy as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> am hear a priſoner at your pleaſure, by the accuſation of one <hi>Cox</hi> (as I underſtand) who is (as <hi>I</hi> conceive) an enemy to the truth, as may appeare by his refuſall, and my non admittance, to diſpute the ſame point whereof <hi>I</hi> am accuſed by him; and for the vindication of that truth hold forth by me, <hi>I</hi> ſhall deſire no favour from you, nor any that have, or ſhall any way accuſe me; and if in caſe <hi>I</hi> have ſpoken any blaſphemy, whereof <hi>I</hi> am accuſed, and now in durance, <hi>I</hi> ſhall willingly and volluntarily, ſuffer puniſhment according to my deſervings: and if it may appear otherwiſe, that then <hi>I</hi> may have reparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for my wrongs ſuſtained. New my deſire is, that you would be pleaſed, to take my own recogniſance to appear at the next Aſſizes, which <hi>I</hi> ſhall be ready, to ſtop the mouthes, (<hi>I</hi> make no doubt) of all gain-ſayers. And as <hi>I</hi> have had the Generalls letter for my quick diſpach of my buſineſſe, that <hi>I</hi> might return ſpeedily to my charge ſo <hi>I</hi> ſhall deſire that favour (as a member of the Army) to be tryed by a generall Councell at warre; where we ſhall heard face to face, not that <hi>I</hi> ſhould deſire any countenance or favour from that honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Court; but that all things ſhould be weighed rightly, in an equall bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, Thus craving your anſwer herein, and rest.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours, FRANCIS FREEMAN.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:117922:20"/>
            <p>This letter being delivered by my man, who craved the Majors anſwer thereunto: the Major returned this anſwer, or to this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, not in writing, but by word of mouth, <hi>that in regard the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of accuſation was of ſo high a nature, and that it was for the king, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he could not take my own recogniſance,</hi> but prayed him to tell me, <hi>that any ſureties ſhould ſerve.</hi> So when I brought my ſureties, I told the Major that I was come to remove on mountain, and I made no doubt but to remove the other. Then he asked me what I did mean? my anſwer was, that I thought he might eaſily underſtand me. Then another ſtanding by demanded of me this queſtion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I could remove that mountain betwixt that and <hi>Lime?</hi> to which I anſwered, no, I could not. And thus tis evident, that by their miſapprehonſions, they have look'd upon my litteral expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons mith a carnall eye. And thus I have truly and plainly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated the truth of this matter.</p>
            <p>Thus having given you a briefe deſcription both of the manner of our diſcourſe, and alſo the manner of their carriage towards me. I ſhall now (by the aſſiſtance of the Almighty) paraphraſe upon each particular, for the clearing of theſe truths, and with as much brevity and perſpecuity, as I may, and ſo leave it to the godly wiſe to judge.</p>
            <p>But before I proceed in the handling of theſe particulars, it will not be amiſſe for me to give you a hint or taſt, of ſome notable paſſages in my journy to the head-quarters at <hi>Winſor,</hi> after my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement, I ſhall give you a true relation thereof. The firſt thing obſervable was at the Town of <hi>Marlburough,</hi> where I met with ſome friends of mine, whom I conceived, their ſpirits would have cloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with that truth, for which I had ſuffered; but having ſome diſcourſe with them touching the ſame point, I found them of a contrary judgement, and after ſome few arguments in debating the matter in queſtion we parted, and (as I conceived) my friends were much diſſatisfied, notwithſtanding they had no knowledge of my former ſufferings, neither did I acquaint them at all there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. And hear you may alſo ſee, that I was not free from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving bitter aſperſions caſt upon me, for there was a Parliament man that over-heard our diſcourſe, unknown to us, who on the next day with ſome of his aſſotiates, fell foul on me, with bitter lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and not only againſt me, but againſt the whole Army of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:117922:21"/>Sectaries, as they call'd us, and raiſed up very ſtrange reports of me, which were both falſe and ſcandalous, yet howſoever I was not much troubled at it, becauſe I knew they did but doe the will of him that ſent them thither, and that truth doth often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times meet with oppoſition: when error and falſe-hood flyes apace, and is ſpread abroad without contradiction.</p>
            <p>And ſo from thence I marched to <hi>Redding,</hi> and lodged that night at the ſigne of the Crown, where I ſaw a viſion of the night, as I lay in my bed. And although moſt men doe account ſuch viſions or dreames, to be but fooliſh fantaſmes, fantaſmes of the brain &amp;c. ye I can aſſure you, that I had moſt ſweet and glorious things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to me in a viſion, <hi>viz.</hi> after ſome few troubles, and ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of ſpirit, I had there preſented unto me, the white ſtone, ſpoken of in the <hi>Revelations, Which noe man knoweth, ſaving he that receiveth it.</hi> But howſoever, before I could have it, I muſt paſſe through ſome difficulties and dangers, for it lay in a garden, under a bed of ſweet flowers, and there was a great brinded Maſtive dog tyed at the garden dore, to keep me from it; yet howſoever, I muſt have it, notwithſtanding all difficulties; and having at that time, ſuch a tranſcendant boldneſſe, that forthwith, I went to the dore, and opened it; the dog looked ſomewhat fiercely upon me, but not ſo much as opened his mouth againſt me; and ſo I went to the bed of flowers, and took up the which ſtone, where I ſaw my name written, and brought it forth with me, the dog looked upon me ſomewhat with an angry countenance, but not ſo much as toucht me, and ſo I came away clearly, with that rich prize I had taken. Now the Bed of flowers, preſented me with the bed of ſpices, ſpoken of in the book of <hi>Canticles:</hi> and the white ſtone preſented unto me, in my apprehenſion, my deliverance notwithſtanding all oppoſition; and ſo I awoke, where I was not altogether ignorant of the viſion which I ſaw, neither was I without ſome teaching in it: for my ſpirit was wonderfully rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up, with ſuch heavenly contemplations, and as it were raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with ſuch divine raptures, and ſpiritual enjoyments, and rejoicyngs, that my ſoul was even lifted up as it were, above the heavens: where I ſaw (as in a glaſſe) all the glory thereof; in that moſt rich, ſweet, and pleaſant paradiſe of God, which the garden here mentioned preſented me withall. And at the apprehenſion
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:117922:21"/>of theſe things, I was ſo tranſcendently carryed up with ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of my deliverance, from all ſuch falſe and ſcandalous ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations; that I awakt my man (lying at my beds feet) to tell him of my dream, and withall the confidence <hi>I</hi> had, that I ſhould be cleared before his Excellency the Lord Generall, notwitſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as I thought at that time, and afterwards it did appear) my advenſarys had ſent a bitter letter of charge againſt me, to render me as odious a they could poſſible. In theſe things, I ſaw my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nituall liberty, and you may alſo ſee the confidence I had of my temporall freedome, much more might be ſpoken, concerning the viſion; the moral of it is good; but I ſhall leave it to your ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous cogitations and contemplations; yet howſoever, Children maſt have bread, and if brinded dogs ſnatch at it, who can help it? to their peril be it, and ſo I haſten on in my journey.</p>
            <p>The Lord (who is wonderfull in Counſel, rules and governs all things by his providence, and diſpoſeth all things, after the Counſel of his own will) carryed me on carefully in my journey towards <hi>Windſor;</hi> and by his providence (near <hi>Maidenhead-Brigde</hi>) I met with Mr. <hi>Peters,</hi> who is an eminent man, aiman of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and exquiſit parts, and of a known integrity. There he told me, That the Magiſtrates of <hi>Taunton,</hi> had ſent a bitter letter of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint againſt me; and the General referred it to him to examine, and to take an account thereof; touching this matter of charge, which he did accordingly; and I gave him, a true and perfect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, firſt, of the manner of our diſcourſe, which the charge had no relation unto. Secondly, the point which I then delivered, and now in queſtion. And thirdly the grounds of my agument proved; which gave himſelf very good ſatisfaction, inſomuch that he ſaid it was a glorious truth, but gave me this caution, that I ſhould not uſe to preach ſuch high things, to poor Ignorant people, that were not able to bear it. To which I anſwered, that it was but a diſcourſe, with one <hi>Cox,</hi> who went under the name and notion of a Miniſter of the Goſpel, and placed in a perſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of 100 pound <hi>per annum</hi> by the <hi>Committee,</hi> and if ſuch ſhould not bear it, who ſhould? his anſwer was, that ſuch as he was, could worſt of all bear it. And ſo he ſpake to me to go back again with him through <hi>Maidenhead,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Windſor</hi> on that ſide the water; which I did, any by the way, I gave him a true relation of the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:117922:22"/>Magiſtrats carriage towards me, inſomuch (as I conceived) he was fully ſatisfied touching my wronges ſuſtained; for he deſired me to come to him immediately after dinner, and he would put me into a way, what courſe to take, ſo when I came to him, he adviſed me to draw a ſhort petition to the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall to referre it to ſome others, as well as himſelf, to hear my anſwer to their charge, and the rather to avoid ſuch ſcandalous imputations, as are apt to be caſt upon us, and withall, he ſpake to me to give the Generall the true relation in writing. So when I preſented my petition, I gave him the very ſame <hi>verbatim,</hi> that is here preſented to your view. And when his Excellency had read the petition, he preſently (out of his pious, and tender care he hath, and alwaies had, for the maintenance of truth, and the lovers thereof, and no way countenancing error or blaſphemy, but altogether for the punniſhment of evil doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well) thought fit to referre it to Lieut. Generall <hi>Hammond,</hi> Colonel <hi>Huſon,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Peters,</hi> to examine me touching each particular of this complaint and to make report according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. They finding my anſwer ſo clear, in reference to our diſcourſe, that they judged me to be much wronged, made the report to the General, and withall Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> moved him for reparations. The Generals anſwer was, that they did it Ignorantly, therefore would not alow me reparations: but wrote his letter to them: a true coppy thereof (as it was tranſcribed by the Generals <hi>Clerk</hi>) as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>SInce the receipt of your letter concerning Captain <hi>Freeman,</hi> he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared at the head quarters, wherein he hath bin examined concerning the particulars aledged againſt him in your letter, and hath given in his anſwer thereunto, and although (for ought that yet appears) the offence taken, was by miſapprehending of ſome unadviſed expreſſions of his, yet <hi>I</hi> am ſo tender of the glory of God, that I ſhall not in the least connive at any blaſphemy or ſuch like impietyes, and therefore deſire, that if any farther charge can be brought againſt him, you will cauſe it to be ſent up to the Iudge-Advocate of the Army, that ſo he (being a member of the Army) may be proſecuted and tried for the ſame at the head-quarters, and in the mean time <hi>I</hi> deſire that his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognizance
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:117922:22"/>may be delivered up, and his ſureties diſcharged.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Windſer</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>11.</hi> Ianuary <hi>1647.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Your aſſured friend FAIRFAX.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Now my Troop being deſigned to quarter at <hi>Winbourne</hi> and <hi>Cranbourn,</hi> in the County of <hi>Dorſet,</hi> and being ſetled in their quarters, I carried down the letter to the Magiſtrates of <hi>Taunton,</hi> according to the ſuperſcription to them directed, and delivered it to Juſtice <hi>Nicolos</hi> in the Majors abſence, (he being at that time in <hi>London</hi>) the Juſtice read the letter, and (as it ſeemed to me) he was ſomewhat troubled at it: and told me he could not withdraw the recognizance, then I asked him, whether he would ſlight the Generals letter, &amp; whether that ſhould be his anſwer? to which he replyed, that he knew not what to ſay; theſe were catching times, and dangerous for him to ſpeak to me. Truly (ſaid I) for my part, I do not deſire to cratch at you, nor at any man elſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though you were very apt to catch at me, by your miſapprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: but I deſire that every man may ſpeak his one judgement freely. Then ſaid Juſtice <hi>Nicolas,</hi> truly Captain <hi>Freeman,</hi> you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered ſtrange points, and indeed points not diſputable, but I am ſure, they are punniſhable. How? not diſputable, and yet pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable? truly (ſaid I) that ſeemeth as ſtrange to me; and if they were ſtrange to you; I am ſure they are truths to me; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all deſired him to conſider of an anſwer, and told him, that I would wait on him the next morning, and ſo took my leave: but it ſeemed to me, that he had ſome whimſies in his head, or ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meroes in his brain, he could not ſtay ſo long, but came immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately to my qurters, and told me, that he did honour the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and his letrer; but he conceived, that I had made the beſt of it for my ſelf, being there was not any to proſecute againſt me: to which I anſwered, that there was their letter of charge againſt me; and I had anſwered to each particular: and if ſo be they had any more to charge me withall, that they had their liberty to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the charge againſt me at a Counſel at warre; according to the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:117922:23"/>Generals letters where they might have a lawful hearing. Then he told me that he would not withdraw my <hi>recognizance,</hi> for the <hi>Major</hi> was at <hi>London</hi> and the book was lockt up, and this was his anſwer, and ſo the Iuſtice and I parted, and ſo I marcht from thence to <hi>Mels</hi> to ſpeak with the <hi>Treaſurer</hi> belonging to the <hi>Committee</hi> of that County; and in the interim, my Cornet received an order, from Colonel <hi>Scroop,</hi> to march with my whole Troop to <hi>Tounton,</hi> and there to quarter till farther orders, and to be aſſiſtant to the Commiſſioners of <hi>Exciſe;</hi> in the mean time, I heard not any thing of my Troopes march, till I came to <hi>Shasbury,</hi> to Colonel <hi>Scroop,</hi> who told me, that my Troop was upon their march towards <hi>Taunton,</hi> and that they were to quarter at <hi>North-petherion</hi> that night, and ſo to march in with the Commiſſioners the next day. I ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that night at <hi>Shasbury,</hi> and received farther orders, from Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Scroop</hi> which were as followeth, that in caſe the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners did not ingage for our quarters, that then we ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to our former quarters. So the next morning, I marcht to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Taunton,</hi> but fell ſhort in my journey, and in the mean time, my Cornet received billets from the Commiſſioners, to quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter my Troop upon the In-holders, &amp; victualers; but the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners durſt not march in with the Troop themſelves, for fear of ſome farther miſchief intended againſt them as they had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly taſted of ſome in part; and the Townſmen gave out (day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) threatening ſpeeches, againſt them (as the Commiſſioners ſaid) that they would uſe them but courſely, and if they came to ſet up the exciſe there, they would beat them out of the town, or beat out their braines, or to this effect; and their intentions ſeemed to be no leſſe (as may appear by my ſouldiers entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) for as they marcht along the freet, the people threw dirt and old ſhoes at them, call'd them exciſe Rogues &amp;c. and told them, they ſhould have no quarter there. My Souldiers did much admire at ſuch courſe entertainment (eſpecially) from ſuch, who pretended themſelves to be for the Parliament, yet under this conſideration, that it was in the height of their <hi>Market,</hi> and that many of them had drunk very hard: therefore they did the more patiently ſuffer ſuch reproachful language at their hands, and ſo repaired to their ſeverall quarters, according to their bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets. But when they came thither, the In-keepers gave them the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:117922:23"/>like entertainment; for generally, as it were with one conſent, they told them, that they ſhould have no quarter there, but for their money. To which my Souldiers anſwered, that they had no money at preſent, for they had received no pay in a long time before, yet gave them good words, and told them, that they had orders to quarter there, and that there would be engagements for payment of their quarters, till they had received pay from the County, but all this would not prevail with them, for they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, and ſaid, that they would take no engagement, but ready money. Then after this divers perſons, both Townſ-men and Country-men came about them, mearly to pick quarrels with them (as it did appeare) for the Souldiers deſired them to be quiet, and told them that they would willingly be ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and quiet in their quarters, yet notwithſtanding, they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued a long time in the ſame way, with ſuch provoking language not to be indured; and about tenne a clock the quarrel burſt forth, great tumults did ariſe at ſeverall houſes, and the rude mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude cryed fall on, fall on, many up in armes, pretending ſome great abuſe, or wrong done by the Souldiers; and cryed out no quarter, no quarter, give the Rogues no quarter. This continued a long time, and my men ſtood upon their own guard in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral quarters, the Townſ-men fell on in divers houſes, at one and the ſame time, ſome wounded on both ſide, and one Townſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man mortally wounded; yet it pleaſed God, ſo to diſpoſe of things, that ſome of the Magiſtrates came amongſt them, and did appeaſe the raging fury of the rude multitude, and perſwaded them to go home to their ſeverall habitations; yet notwitſtanding they would not preſently deſilt, their malice was ſuch towards me, undeſervedly, that they would draw out a for-lorn-hope, as they eall'd it, of thirty or fourty men, to ſearch for me in ſeveral houſes, and ſwore that they vvould beat out my brains, for my Troop vvas come of purpoſe, to revenge my former quarrel. But from vvhence this came, I ſhall leave it to your thoughts. But this vvas the Relation given by my Cornet and Souldiers, as near as I could take it, vvhen I came thither, vvhich vvas on the next morning, but by the vvay, as I vvent to the Tovvn, I met vvith tvvo of my Souldiers, vvhich my Cornet had ſent to Col. <hi>Scroop</hi> to inform him of theſe paſſages; vvho gave me the very ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:117922:24"/>and vvithall advertiſed me not to go into the Tovvn, for theſe reaſons aforementioned, but my reſolution vvas to truſt to providence, and ſo made haſt: and vvhen I came thither, I vvent immediately, to Juſtice <hi>Nicolas</hi> his houſe; vvhere I found the reſt of the Magiſtrates in conſultation with him, concerning this tumult and mutinie; and after ſome conference with them, I found that there was a foule miſcariage of the buſineſſe, by the Commiſſioners, but yet the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> laid the greateſt blam on my Souldiers, to excuſe their own Townſ-men, as if they had been in no fau't, who were as I conceived, the prime actors, and chief mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineers in this horrible combuſtion; and as it did appear to me by divers circumſtances they had great abitters on, but howſoever finding their temper, I deſired the Magiſtrates to draw over the billits again, and took them the book, called the <hi>addiſſional dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions;</hi> that ſo they might quarter my Souldiers according to thoſe directions, which they cauſed the Conſtables accordingly to do it; but we found a generall averſeneſſe to the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Parliament in that caſe provided. Then I offered my ſelfe to engage for their quarters, their anſwer was generally, throughout the whole Town, that they would not take my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, nor the Magiſtrates neither. Then <hi>I</hi> made Juſtice <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colas</hi> acquainted with it, and ſhewed him our condition, that ſome of my men were walking up and down the ſtreets at that time of night without any quarters, then the juſtice went along with me, and put them into their houſes: and deſired them to give them enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment for that night, but he found it to be true, for they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered us plainly, that they would not take both our Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. The I told the Juſtice, that in caſe the Commiſſioners came not in the next morning, to engage for our quarters, and ſo put their commiſſion in excution, that I would march forth of the Town by twelve a clock the next day; but as we were talking together, there came ſome Townſ men to us, to demand juſtice, the Juſtice asked them, what they would have? one of them made anſwer, that they would have the Souldier ſecured, that had mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally wounded his brother, for he lay a dying; Then Juſtice <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colas</hi> ſaid, Captain <hi>Freeman,</hi> it concernes you to doe them Juſtice, and if you will not, then <hi>I</hi> muſt. To which I anſwered, that it did altogether concern me to do juſtice upon my Souldiers, if they
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:117922:24"/>did offend; and that it did no way concern him at all. And if ſo be they could ſhew me the man which they accuſed, then they ſhould ſee me do them juſtice. Then they told me, that he was at the ſign of the Caſtle, ſo when we came thither, they laid it to my Drumers charge: ſo I preſently ſecured him, and withall ſent to the Governour of the Caſtle, to deſire him, that I might ſend him into the Caſtle, to be upon his guard for that might, for ſome reaſons beſt known to my ſelfe, which was granted by him, ſo on the next morning I ſent for him forth again, and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him into my Corporals cuſtodie in my own chamber, and ſo ſtayed till about twelve a clock, and finding that the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners, durſt not come in to engage for our quarters, I cauſed my Trumpet to ſound to horſe, and my Cornet drew the Souldiers into the market-place, and ſo marcht to the place oppointed for the randeſvouz, at the Townſ-end till farther orders.</p>
            <p>Now my Troop being marcht forth, I having no thoughts of any more trouble, I went to ſpeake with the Governour of the Caſtle, where I met in my way the rude multitude flocking to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, who preſently ſeiſed on me; and told me that I had ſent a way the priſoner, and that they could not have juſtice, therefore they would ſecure me, till I had ſent for him again; my anſwer was, that I had done them juſtice, for I had ſecured him, and that he was in my Corporals Cuſtody, in my chamber at my quarters. And that it did concern me carefully to ſee him forthcoming, for he muſt be tryed by a councel at warre. But they cryed out, no, no, he ſhould not be tryed by a Councel at warre; but at the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſizes; and therefore I muſt leave him behinde me a priſoner, and ſo I went back to my quarters, with the multitude about me, where they ſaw him a priſoner, yet notwithſtanding, all this would not give them ſatisfaction, but they would have him into the Caſtle again, I ſaw that it was but a folly for me to go about to reſiſt their wills, told them they ſhould have their deſire in it, and ſo had him to the Caſtle, and there left him; and then I thought I ſhould have bin quit of this tumultuous crue, but they would not be ſo quit of me; for then they began to pick another quarel with me, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding of me by what order my Troop marcht thither? Leiut. Colonel <hi>Buffit</hi> coming by us, by accident, told them, that I had an order ſufficient; and that he had ſeen it, which gave them ſuch
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:117922:25"/>ſatisfaction, inſomuch that they drew away from me by degrees, not having any thing elſe to ſay to me. Now all this while, not ſo much as a Magiſtrate or Townſ-man of any faſhion (but the Lieutenant Colonel) that ever came near me, neither indeed would any of them be ſeen, any way to ſtop this tumult, till by a providence it was quite over, as if they had been willing to ſuffer them to act their Maſters will, in making good their former vows and Proteſtations; for this being no ſooner paſt over, but preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I met with the Governour, Juſtice <hi>Nicolas</hi> and the two <hi>Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> and told them of theſe abuſes; to which the Juſtice anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſaid, that they were a rude people, and he could not help it. And ſo they went along with me to my quarters, to ſee me take horſe; and told me, they would give me a pint of wine, and when we came thither, the Governour and I had ſome conference, concerning the priſoner; but he concluded with me that he muſt be tryed by a councel of War, and ſaid that he ſhould not be a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner in the Caſtle, but told me, that it concerned me to ſee him forth-coming; and ſo ſent a file of muſqueteers for him, and when he was brought before us, he pleaded his innocency, and ſaid, that if the man dyed of his wounds, that he was not guilty of his <hi>death,</hi> for he vvas never in that houſe at all vvhere he vvas vvounded; and vvithall, deſired us, that he might go to ſee the dying man, and ſpeak vvith him, for he vvas confident, that he vvould not lay it to his charge, but rather clear him, if he vvere ſenſible. We finding his vvillingneſſe, to ſpeake vvith the wounded man, granted his deſire; and the Juſtice, the tvvo Conſtables, and the guard vvent along vvith him, and vvhen they came to him, they firſt ſet before him a Souldier of the guard, and asked him vvhether that vvere the man that hurt him? I ſaid he, that is the Rogue that hath killed me: no, no, ſaid the Juſtice, that is one of the Caſtle-Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers; and then ſet before him three Souldiers more (vvhereof my Drummer vvas one) &amp; then asked him vvhether either of them vvere the man? he anſvvered no; the man that hurt him had flaxen coloured hair, and a little beard; and ſo my Drummer vvas cleared by him: for indeed he vvas a very youth, and had no beard at all, nor ſuch colloured hair, as he deſcribed, but a ſad brown colour. And ſo they returned to my quarters, where we drunk two or three pints of wine, and the Juſtice would not ſuffer me to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:117922:25"/>pay for any; but did proteſt, that notwithſtanding we differ'd in judgment, yet for my part ſaid he I cannot lay any blam upon you for your carriage in this buſineſſe, but I muſt withdraw your re-cogniſance, and there is an end of it; and ſeemed to be loving and kind to me, and ſo we parted, and I marcht with my Troop to <hi>Midleſea</hi> and <hi>Autry,</hi> and quartered there that night. The next day I received a letter from the Commiſſioners, to deſire me to meet the Sheriffe and them, with a Troop of Colonel <hi>Scroops</hi> horſe at <hi>Taunton</hi> the next morning, which I did accordingly, and when the Sheriff read the Commiſſion in the Market place, ſome of the chief mutiniers ſtood by, what their intentions were I leave it for you to judge, but ſome of them were ſeized on, and impriſoned; and then the Town (with much ado) ſubmitted to the Ordinance of Parliament, and ſome whom I conceived were my greateſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, became humble petitioners to me, to ſpeake for them to the Commiſſioners; which I profes I did out of a real intention to do them good: and Juſtice <hi>Nicolas</hi> did acknowledge it, that I had earneſtly ſolicited for them, and not only for them but in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the whole Town.</p>
            <p>But now you ſhall ſee how I was requited for this ſervice, and not only for this, but for all other ſervices done in the County, for the firſt newes I heard from the head quarters was, that Juſtice <hi>Nicolas,</hi> with the reſt of the Magiſtrals had ſent up another bitter letter of complaint againſt me to the General, ſignifying unto him that I had ſent in my Troop without order, mearly to be reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on them for the former quarrel; and that many ſtirrs and tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults did ariſe by that means, and abundance of miſchiefe done in the Town &amp;c. This letter was preſented to the General by the Major of <hi>Taunton,</hi> who came from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Windſor</hi> for the very ſame ourpoſe, &amp; not only to charge me with that baſe letter of falſ accuſation, but did alſo exceedingly agravate the former buſineſſe, and wonderfully inſenced the Generall againſt me, inſomuch, that ſome Officers, which were preſent at that time, have told me ſince, that they never ſaw the Generall in ſuch a rage in their lives: and that he ſaid that he was reſolved to puniſh whereſoever the fault lay. Now touching this matter of falſe accuſation: Colonel <hi>Scroop</hi> can witneſſe my innocency, and hath already certyfied the Generall the truth of this matter, and that I had done nothing that he could find without order from him.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:117922:26"/>
            <p>But as envy and malice, ſeldome, or never lies long hid, but that it muſt of neceſſity break forth: ſo they have manifeſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, their imbittred ſpirits againſt me, by proſecuting their former deſigns; for they have (ſince that time) indicted me at the the Aſſizes: and proſecuted the indictment, with as much force and vigor as they could poſſibly: not having any relation at all to our former diſcourſe; inſomuch, that the Grand-jury found the bill, and my enemies do exceedingly rejoyce at it. Therefore, I have thought it requiſit and neceſſary, to give you a true and perfect Journal of theſe paſſages betwixt us, that I may the better make way for your underſtanding of theſe things herein contained, and if ſo be that any of my adverſaries ſhould have that impudency, to deny any one particular, herein expreſſed: I ſhall be able to clear it, by the teſtimony of honeſt men; and ſhall humbly refer it to the ſerious conſideration of the judicious reader; to judge of their dealings towards me; and ſo proceed in the proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of each particular in order. And firſt, of the firſt, which is touching the manner of our diſcourſe.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ground of my Argument lies thus.</head>
               <p>That he that hath faith, he is in Chriſt, and Chriſt in him: ſo that faith is Chriſt manifeſted in him, and he is Chriſt, though not eſſentially; yet in reſpect of that ſpirituall oneneſſe with him, and in him, <hi>Iohn</hi> 17. ſo that there can be no ſeparation nor divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, betwixt the head and members, in regard of that ſpirituall union and oneneſſe. And as there is that ſpiritual union and oneneſſe, that cannot admit of any ſeparation, or deviſion, ſo I ſhall handle the branches thereof (iſſuing or flowing from them, as ſtreams from a fountain) both jointly and ſeverally, in regard of that near relation and conjunction, betwixt the head and members.</p>
               <p>But firſt we are to conſider, that there is a relative union, and there is a reall union; which I ſhall ſhew you, under a two-fold conſideration, yet comparatively (in my apprehenſion) they are both as one, 1. This relative union is, as the husband and wiſe, Chriſt and his Church. And this reall union is, as the tree and branches, and if ſo be a branch of that tree be cut off it is no longer a branch of that tree (being diſunited) although it retains the ſame quality for a while in regard of its own nature; yet it ſoon withers and dies, although the body lives and growes: now
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:117922:26"/>this relative union with Chriſt and his Church, is ſuch a union, that they are ſo inſeparably united and knit together, with that ſpirituall bond of love and amity, that can never be broken. For our Saviour Chriſt ſaith, that he is the vine, and ye are the branches, and if ſo b e a member of Chriſt (which is a branch of that vine) be cut off, by a corporal or temporal death, yet the ſpirit retaines its firſt principles, and returnes to God that gave it; and ſpritually, it continues, and remaines a branch of that royall ſtock; For as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>that neither life, nor death, nor things preſent, nor things to come; ſhall be able to ſeperate us from the love of God, which is in Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> ſo that here we ſee, that this is that ſpiritual union and oneneſſe: not that the body is the head, or the head the body; but that all the members, (as branches) make up but one body, whereof Chriſt is the head. And they are a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect body in Chriſt, ſo that there needs no ſupply of any thing to make them a perfect body, for their is nothing wanting to make them compleat; as there may be wanting in the naturall body of man, for if there be but a little finger wanting, or but one joynt of that little finger, it is an imperfect body, ſo that the eye cannot ſay to the hand, I have no need of thee, nor the head to the feet, I have no need of you, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.21. But in this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual body of Chriſt, it is otherwiſe: for the fleſh was crucified at Jeruſalem: and as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. <hi>I am crucified with Chriſt, nevertheleſſe I live, yet not</hi> I, <hi>but Chriſt liveth in me. And they that are Chriſts, have crucified the fleſh, with the affections and luſts Gal.</hi> 5.24. And as Chriſt is head over his Church: ſo God hath put all things under his feet, and gave him to be head over all things to the church, which is his body, the fullneſſe of him that filleth all in all, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.22, 23. Chriſt is all and in all (by hit providence) to every creature: but he is all and in all, in a more ſpeciall and peculiar manner (by his providence) to his Saints, which are his Church. So that there can be no ſeparation nor deviſion, betwixt the head and members.</p>
               <p>And for a farther illuſtration and conformation of this truth in hand (I ſpeak chiefly to you, who are friends, and lovers of truth) I ſhall commend to your ſerious conſideration theſe ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures following (to wit) <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.5, 6. <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.16. Where you ſhall finde in the former Chap. <hi>The Lord ſpeaking to the Iſraelites, of a
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:117922:27"/>righteous branch, that he would raiſe unto David, and that a King ſhould reign and proſper &amp;c. In his daies Judah ſhall be ſaved, and Iſrael ſhall dwell ſafely, and this is his name whereby he ſhall be called,</hi> The LORD OUR RIGHTEOUSNES. Now this righteous branch is meant Chriſt, who is the King of Saints, and he ſhall proſper, in the gathering together of his Saints, from the uttermoſt parts of the earth, even amongſt the heathen, nay the heathens them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.8. and this is done out of his abundant love to his poor creatures. <hi>And here he is called, the Lord our Righteouſnes,</hi> and in the 33. Chap. of the ſame book of <hi>Jer.</hi> before mentioned, verſe 16. there you ſhall finde, a kind of reciprocall love, by way of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changes of loves, betwixt Chriſt and his Church; where he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours his church with his own name, and in the very ſelf ſame ſweet expreſſion, The lord our Righteouſneſſe; ſo that every particular member hath an intereſt in this name: as you may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by this Scripture following, which is (as I conceive) a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of this truth, ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.3. where it is ſaid; that the head of every man is Chriſt: ſo that every particular member, is Chriſt, not eſſentially: not that the body is the head, or the head the body; but under this twofold conſideration, 1. In regard of that ſpiritual oneneſſe with him, and in him: and 2. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his name, wherewith he ſhall be called, The Lord our Righteouſneſſe; which is here ſpoken of the church. And you may ſee in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>That he that is jayned unto the Lord, is one ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now if ſo be, I had ſaid, that I had bin the Chriſt, then cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly I had ſpoken blaſphemy in the higheſt degree, and my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaryes, might have had juſt cauſe againſt me, and that ſcripture had bin fulfilled in me, that in the latter times, there ſhall ariſe many falſe Chriſts &amp;c. but I hope (in the handling of this point) I have made it ſo clear, and ſo plaine to the weakeſt capacity, that they cannot but plead my innocency and integrity, and ſo I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the next in order; which is touching faith, what ſaith is, according to my former diſcourſe, and the ground of my argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments laid down.</p>
               <p>Therefore to prove the point, that faith is Chriſt; See <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.23. Where Chriſt is called faith, the words are theſe in the hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry according to the letter. <hi>But before faith came; we were kept under
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:117922:27"/>the law &amp;c.</hi> But in the myſtery, and according to the ſpirituall ſence (in my apprehenſion) faith is there meant Chriſt, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt came, we were kept under the law, ſhut up unto the fiath which ſhould afterwards be revealed. This word, but, hath reference to the former verſes, therefore read from the 21. verſe to the end of the <hi>chap.</hi> and you may find this (if God ſays Amen to it) to be a glorious truth; But if ſo be, you have but a notionall knowledge of Chriſt, or a bare hiſtorical faith: as Mr. <hi>Cox</hi> by his expreſſions (in anſwer to my queſtion.) did import no other; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he did hope he had faith, which is but hiſtorical, by hearſay and mearly the teachings of men, and no otherwiſe; then you cannot ſay of a truth, that Chriſt is in you, the hope of glory. <hi>Theſe things have</hi> I <hi>written unto you, concerning them that ſeduce you. But if you have received the anointing, it abideth in you, and the ſame anointing, teacheth you of all things; and is truth, and is no ly &amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Job.</hi> 2.26, 27. And if Chriſt be in you, the hope of glory; then you ſhall finde that ſpirituall and individual ſubſtance, or rather ſubſiſtance (in reſpect of operations) manifeſted within you, that is infeperable, For we are his anointing, and that ſpiritual unction within us, makes us to be one with him. We are Kings, and Prieſts, and by vertue of his ſpiritual anointing, we are one with him, by faith (which is Chriſt in us) we apprend all the benefits, and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all enjoyments and rejoycings, made out unto us: and by his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual deſcenſion ſo low into us; and drawing us up into himſelf; we are come to be one with him, and in him, and he in us. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. being iuſtified by faith in his blood. And as there is ſuch a ſweet union, and oneneſſe between Chriſt and the ſoul; Chriſt being the manifeſtation of his fathers love: the ſoul comes to have free acceſſe by one ſpirit unto the Father, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.18. in and through the Son; whereby the ſoul comes to ſee God, purely as he is: ſo that there is a continual feaſt of fat things, their Table being richly deckt, and covered over with all ſorts of varieties of dainties; ſupping and dining together. And there is a continual preſence, or habit of union between God and the ſoul: that the ſoul is (as it were) richly clothed with God; and God with the ſoul, do live mutually in themſelves, for, he that dwels in love, dwels in God &amp; God in him, &amp; that nothing is in God, that is not God, therefore whatſoever is in God is God. And thus the ſoul
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:117922:28"/>comes to ſee God to be his all and in all, and ſees him in all things, &amp; in every thing, and ſees his own nothingneſſe and emptyneſſe, of himſelf without him.</p>
               <p>But now I ſhall ſhew you that there are many who look upon Chriſt after the fleſh, and not after the ſpirit, or a ſpiritual Chriſt within us (not apprehending him as he is purely in himſelf) ſo they look upon the act of faith, to be that which God accepts to juſtification. But truly (for my part) I am not of that judgement; for I conceive, there is a miſtake in it, looking upon him after the fleſh, and not after the ſpirit, or in the ſpirit: and ſo they aſſeribe that honour to faith, which is due unto Chriſt, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour him in ſo doing: for although they do not exclude Chriſt wholly and totally; yet in the act of juſtification (which is a work) it gives all unto faith, we are juſtified before God in his ſight, only by Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20.24. and for a farther confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this truth, ſee <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.11, 12. Where it is ſaid, my righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſervant ſhall juſtifie many, which muſt be underſtood of Chriſt. we are not juſtified before God, by faith which is in us; but by Chriſt, by his blood. We are juſtified by his blood. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.9. by faith, which is Chriſt in us, we know our ſelves to be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, verſe firſt: and although faith is one of the chiefeſt graces: yet as it is an act, it is a work, and to be juſtified by it, is to be juſtified by a work of our own, for with the heart (man) beleeveth <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.9, 10. ſo that tis clear, that which juſtifie us, muſt needs be perfect; and ſo it can be no act of ours; for all our righteouſneſſes are as filthy ragges &amp;c, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.6. <hi>not of works, leaſt any ſhould boaſt, Ephe.</hi> 2.9. Me thinks the conſideration of this point ſhould cauſe us to admire at the wonderful riches of the free grace of God in Chriſt Jeſus, who out of his infinite love, being an infinite glorious Majeſty, that he ſhould deſcend ſo low, as to take upon himſelfe our nature (being poor finite creatures) to ſhed his blood, to die for us, and to riſe again for our juſtification. But that his eſſential will is himſelf, his power is himſelf, his <hi>wiſdome</hi> is himſelf, and every thing that is in him, is himſelf, <hi>if we can but ſee it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to proceed a little farther in the proſecution of this point of faith. I ſhall ſpeak ſomething concerning <hi>Enochs</hi> walking with God by faith, and ſo conclude the point.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.24. <hi>That Enoch walked with God, and was not; for
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:117922:28"/>God took him.</hi> By faith he was Tranſlated, that he ſhould not ſee death &amp;c. And the text ſaith, that <hi>he was one that is not;</hi> this may ſeem to be a paradox, a ſtrange expreſſion, if we but barely look upon the letter of the Scripture; yet it is a glorious truth; for it is ſaid, <hi>he is one that is not. Enoch walked with God, and was not.</hi> So that he walked not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit; for he was tranſlated by faith, that he ſhould not ſee death, and was not found, <hi>he was not, for God took him.</hi> He in himſelf was not; for his glory and excellency paſt away, all his earthly pomps vaniſh'd, he of himſelf was nothing, for he ſaw his own emptineſſe and nothingneſſe, and all-ſufficiency in Chriſt: what he was, he was in Chriſt, Chriſt was his life, and his all, <hi>Chriſt was all and in all</hi> unto him, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.11. So that God tranſlated <hi>Enoch</hi> in the ſpirit, he was tranſlated into Jeſus Chriſt; and ſo every true believer is one in Jeſus Chriſt, and nothing in himſelf; there is a glorious change; there is a new birth, there is a new ſelf, he is born of God; God is his ſelfe, Chriſt is his ſelf. So that <hi>Enoch</hi> was out of the fleſh, into the ſpirit, out of himſelf and his own righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, into God; and ſo is every saint, every true believer is tranſlated out of himſelf, into a being which is in God. He is dead unto all ſelf-righteouſneſſe, he is dead unto the law, he is dead unto the World, but he is alive unto God: Here you ſee that by faith <hi>Enoch</hi> was Tranſlated from death to life: Therefore you may ſee that faith is an excellent gift, <hi>eſt donum Dei,</hi> it is the gift of God, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.8. And ſo all things elſe that are given, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from him, but this gift of faith in a more ſpecial manner, becauſe Chriſt is given in it by believing; but I ſhall ſhew you that there are degrees of faiths manifeſtation in believing according to the apprehenſion, ſome degrees more weake, ſome more ſtrong. Yet if thou haſt but <hi>faith as a grain of muſtard-ſeed, thou ſhalt be able to remove Mountains,</hi> which is the next particular to be handled. But a word or two more touching the higheſt degree of faith, which is faiths aſſurance, aſſurance being the proper act of faith, proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the reflect act of faith, which cauſeth a man to know and ſee that he beleeves; and this aſſurance is from the immediate teſtimony of the ſpirit of God in the conſcience of him who is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready a believer; and cauſeth the ſoul to know that it believes, <hi>The ſpirit it ſelf beareth witneſſe with our ſpirits</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16. But ſo
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:117922:29"/>much ſhall ſuffice for this point, the next in order, is that moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to be removed; according to the main drift and ſcope of my argument.</p>
               <p>Firſt, a mountain in Scripture; is taken divers waies, as you may find in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2. <hi>Mark</hi> 11. &amp;c. But I ſhall ſhew you, firſt Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, What a mountain is not. Secondly, affirmatively, What it is. And according to the reall drift and ſcope of my meaning at the diſcourſe; and it ſo be the Magiſtrates (with patience) could have heard me make it forth, I ſhould have cleared it, but that they would ſcarce ſuffer me to ſpeak for my ſelf; but ſearcht the ſtatute-book to ſee what puniſhment was fit for blaſphemers, in that caſe provided; taking his accuſation for truth, not knowing how, or in what manner I had declared my ſelf, neither could they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand my meaning touching this mountain here ſpoken of. Therefore I ſhew you. 1. Negatively, that I did not mean ſuch a Mountain as that great hill neer <hi>Taunton,</hi> called by the name of <hi>black-down,</hi> according to the queſtion propounded unto me. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did I mean that great round Cob-hill call'd by the name of <hi>Glaſtonburytor.</hi> Nor that great mountain of Saint <hi>Taffies,</hi> in <hi>Welch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Nor had I any thoughts of removing that great hill of <hi>Taun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> out of his place, (who was then <hi>Major pro tempore</hi>) and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me to priſon, when as neither of them knew a mountain from a mole-hill. But I ſpeake this but by the way, and therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be excuſed. 2. Affirmatively, There are mountaines with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us as well as mountains without us; there are mountains of ſin, and there are mountains of oppoſition, there are mountains of power, and there are mountains of pride and ſelf-loftineſſe, there are mountains of oppreſſion and Tyranny &amp;c. An indeed every thing is a mountain that exalts it ſelf, or is exalted high in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to truth. As you may ſee in the aforecited chapter from verſe 10. and ſo forwards; but yet all theſe mountains ſhall be lay'd low, when <hi>the lofty looks of men ſhall be humbled, and the haughtineſſe of men ſhall be bowed down, and the Lord alone ſhall be exalted in that day.</hi> Which is the day of Gods power. But what fleſh ſhall abide his coming? When he ſhall come <hi>as a refiners fire, and like fullers ſope,</hi> when all corruption ſhall be burnt up, and be deſtroyed, or at leaſt be cleanſed and purified from the droſſe, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. <hi>Theſe things are, and ſhall be tranſ-acted in us; but the end is not yet.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:117922:29"/>
               <p>And now friends, although I have not handled every particular circumſtance of this matter in hand, yet every material point of any moment is cleared. Therefore I ſhall now give a word or two in general to the Nations: and chiefly to Magiſtrates and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, and ſuch as are placed in authority over us, which ſhall be by way of good cuncel if you can take it. But if ſo be you do not take it: it will be, becauſe you cannot. Yet nevertheleſſe I have thought good to give you a cautional hint of ſome ſpecial obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, which I have taken, touching the ſeveral greevances of the people, who ly under many greevous preſſures and burdens, and expect relief and comfort from you, which will be by preſcribing wholeſome laws, according to the preſent conſtitution of this Nation, and a due execution thereof, as it was before the Norman Conqueſt. For you know, that the people have lived under a Kingly power, many hundred years, and have been held in bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age and ſlavery ever ſince the conqueſt, under thoſe lawes, which were preſcribed by an Uſurper. And have been ſtill kept under the <hi>Normand</hi> yoak: by reaſon of an abſolute arbitrary power, domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neering over them; raiſed up by <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Conquetor,</hi> when he had ſubdued this Nation by the ſword. Then thoſe who were his Creatures, his favourits, he created them to be Lords of <hi>Mannors</hi> and ſo divided and diſtributed the Land amongſt themſelves, and the poor people, to become tenants unto them, and to pay a ſmall rent at firſt: to bring them under the yoak, and ſo to acknowledge them to be their Lords and maſters; and hence came in that which we call propriety, as derived from the <hi>Norman</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</p>
               <p>Now after this, theſe great Lords. of Mannors, by marriages, matching their Sonnes and daughters together joyn'd houſe to houſe, and land to land, and ſo became greater Lords then ever, and exhauſted greater rents from their poor tenants by degrees: and all to uphold them in their pride, and ſo to maintain them in their pomp and vanities, and Lordly dignities. And ſo the poor people comes to be meer ſlaves to their Lords and Maſters (their rents being continually raiſed and ſet upon the rack, and tenter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoocks of their wicked conſciences) and are not able to maintain themſelves and families, though at a pittyful poor low rate, both in food and rayment, notwithſtanding all their labour and pains<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:117922:30"/>both early and late. But I muſt tell you, that the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainance of propriety in this way, and by ſuch lawes, will be the deſtruction of it; and me thinks, I ſee it already deſtroyed, and you know that the ſtander-by ſometimes ſees more then the gameſter.</p>
               <p>And truly for my part I ſee an exceeding unequal diſtribution of things, ſome all, and ſome nothing at all: and the poor daily crying out for bread, bread, bread for the Lords ſake and few, or none, laying it to heart, when many of your great Lords, have ten, fifteen, twenty thouſand pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> which is more then two hundred thouſand families have: and yet they can ſpend all in rioteouſneſſe, and wantonneſſe, and in ſuperfluity of dainties, and in the delights and pleaſures of this world, and truly I do beleeve, I ſpeak with the leaſt (though I ſpeak it with much grief) that for every one that hath but ten thouſand pounds <hi>per annum.</hi> there are two hundred thouſand families and more, that have not ſo much, and ſo proportionable of all the reſt. I ſpeak from experience of my late travels in the North, where I have ſeen multitudes of poor people go bare-footed and bare-leg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and ſcarce a ragge of clothes, to cover their nakedneſſe, or having any bread, or any kind of food, to put into their bellies, to keep them from ſtarving. And ask the poor people, whoſe land they lived in? or who was their Land-lord? they would tell us, that it was either the Earl of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> or the Lord <hi>Gray:</hi> and now lay this home to your conſciences, and acquaint you with the pittiful condition of theſe poor people; and ask you, where is the feeding of the hungry, and clothing of the naked? you will be ready to anſwer me, as I have bin already anſwered, that the Earl of <hi>Northumberland</hi> or the Lord <hi>Gray</hi> ſhould look to them, and make proviſion for them, as if it did not concern you at all, and will be ready to poſt it off, from poſt to pillar, and ſay, you have poor enough of your own, and that you ought to take care for them. But is it not as much neglected by you, as by them? for, is there not daily crying out in your ſtreets, for bread, bread, for the Lords ſake, not only in this City, but in the countrey alſo, by many thouſands of poor people, who are ready to periſh with famine, and few or none take pitty on them, as to releeve them, but are ready to beat them from your doors (notwithſtanding) they are
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:117922:30"/>fleſh of your fleſh, blood of your blood, and bone of your bone? And all this proceeds from the hardneſſe of your hearts, and from pride and ſelf-loftines, from whence comes oppreſſion and cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and are there not grievious burdens, and taxes, lying heavy upon the people; which cauſeth a dearth upon all things notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding there is great plenty of all in the Land, and who ſuffers but the poor? who are your fellow-creatures, whoſe cries are already aſcended up into heaven before the Almighty: who is able to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due all powers, and to bring down all the proud and lofty ones to ſubmit to his foot-ſtool, and to ly proſtrate at his feet: and may you not juſtly tremble at that terrible doom and ſentence of our Saviour to ſuch, as you ſhew your ſelves to be, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41.42.43. <hi>Depart from me, ye curſed &amp;c. For I was bungry, and ye gave me no meat; I was thirſty, and ye gave me no drink: I was a ſtranger; and ye took me not in, naked: and ye clothed me not, ſick and in priſon, and ye viſited me not;</hi> And may not the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> 5.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. thunder a ratling peal of terror in your ears, Go to now ye rich men, weep and howle &amp;c. ſee <hi>Micah</hi> 2.2. <hi>Micah</hi> 3.1, 2, 3. and <hi>Amos</hi> 6. from the 1. to the 7. read theſe Scriptures conſiderately, and weigh them well, and then I ſhall give ye my Counſel and adviſe, for a remedy (ſpeaking after the mannor of men) which ſhall be firſt to you Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and Governours, who are placed in authority over us, who ſit at the helme, and ought to ſteere all things aright, according to equitie and juſtice.</p>
               <p>That ſeeing all thoſe lawes which came in by the Norman-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and have continued ever ſince, ſucceſſively by Kings, and conſequently by Tyrants, till the late Kings head was taken off; which laws (for the ſubſtance) are ſtill in uſe, as if that he were yet alive, only the form altered. But my Counſel is that they may be wholly taken away, and wholeſome laws preſcribed in the room, that the people may no longer ly under that yoke, which is an intolerable burden. For many families have bin utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, by long and weariſome journies, and by their vaſt expence of mony in their long and tedious ſuits, and by the corruption of the lawyers, which (corruption) will never be taken away: unleſſe the lawes be wholly taken away, both root and branch. And if ſo be you ſhould go about to mend theſe lawes, and have them tranſlated into the <hi>Engliſh</hi> tongue; and divide the Nation
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:117922:31"/>into ſeveral provinces: to avoid tediouſneſſe of travelling; yet the ſame lawes being put in execution (though they are tranſlated as aforeſaid) the corruption will ſtill rmeain, and the people will ſtill ly under the yoke.</p>
               <p>Therefore my Counſel is, that you will wholly take away all the lawes in one day, and give us ſuch wholeſome lawes the next, that may ſtand moſt conſiſtent with the republique, which will be moſt ſuitable to what they were before the Norman Conqueſt.</p>
               <p>Let there be a Court of Judicature erected in each hundred of every County, where cauſes may be equally determined by twelve ſworn men, <hi>annually</hi> choſen by the freemen of the ſaid hundred, and not left to depend upon the prerogative lawyers for juſtice, the obſtructors of the peoples freedomes. And you know there can be no men able to judge ſo well of cauſes and controverſies between partie and party; as ſuch as are neighbours to the parties where the offence or treſpaſſe was committed, and ſo thoſe twelve men to be their Judges to hear and determine, as in time paſt before the Conqueſt the Jury were the Judges, and ended all controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, that were amongſt the people. This being one parcel of good Counſel if ye can take it.</p>
               <p>Now the next <hi>Counſel</hi> I ſhal give you, is, that this unjuſt and into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable burthen of Tythes may be wholly taken away, that thoſe who go under the notion of Miniſters, may live on Goſpel main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainance, and not by law. Seeing it is a more bleſſed thing to give, then to receive; that no man be compelled to maintain ſuch a generation of men, who look to their own way, every one for his own advantage, and for his own purpoſe. Who bite with their teeth, and cry peace, and he that puteth not into their mouth, they even prepare warre againſt him, as we have had ſad experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of them, <hi>being the greateſt incendiaries againſt us &amp; the publick good</hi> of this Nation ever ſince the beginning of theſe troubles. For the firſt warre was the Biſhops warre, and you know that the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie had a great hand in the ſecond warre; labouring to ſet the people againſt both Parliament and <hi>Army,</hi> crying out againſt them almoſt in every pulpit. But when they ſaw, that there was a riſing in <hi>Wales,</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> and that the <hi>Scots</hi> had invaded the Nation, and were ſetting up the Kings intereſt again, and knew full well, that they ſhould be no gainers thereby, then as they had faced about to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:117922:31"/>the left before, ſo they could face about again to the right, as they were, like good ſouldiers. And you know that this warre is the <hi>Kirks</hi> warre, and the Clergie have the greateſt ſhare therein, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out againſt errors, hereſies and blaſphemies, as if they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and none but them, were able to judge what hereſie and blaſphemy is, and as if they were of ſuch infallible judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that whatſoever they ſhall ſay is hereſie or blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie it muſt of neceſſity be ſo. And thus much more I ſhall tell you, that whenſoever the Lord ſhall be pleaſed to give our Army victory over our enemies in <hi>Scotland,</hi> both <hi>Kirke</hi> and State (which I know they muſt be overcome) for that intereſt can never be ſet up again, neither in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> nor <hi>Ireland</hi>) but I ſay that whenſoever that warre is over, you ſhall have the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy be ready to foment another warre preſently, unleſſe you take them off of their great power, which will he done by taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way Tythes, and not compelling, any to maintain them, but thoſe that will have them to be their Miniſters let them maintain them; and let ſuch as are under Goſpel-diſpenſations, be freed from the ſlavery and bondage of legal adminiſtrations. And this is good Counſel if you can take it.</p>
               <p>But here I ſhall meet with an objection by the way. You will aske me (eſpecially you that have impropriations) what will become of you and your families if Tythes go down; you or your predeceſſors laid out all the ſtock you had, to purchaſe an impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priation, and you have not a ſubſiſtance without it. And if it be taken away, you are utterly undone, and your poſterity: ſhall you that have purchas'd looſe your bargain, and your money too; and thoſe that never purchaſed ſhall they have it for nothing?</p>
               <p>I anſwer no, every man ſhall purchaſe the tenth of his own poſſeſſions, of the State: and ſhall pay to the utmoſt value of it, according to ſo many years purchaſe, <hi>viz.</hi> every delinquent four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years purchaſe, every Neuter tenne years purchaſe, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very faithful honeſt man to the State, &amp; can approve himſelf to be ſo; let him have it at five years purchaſe. And by this means you may but in all the impropriations, according to their purchaſe, and ſo give full ſatisfaction accordingly, which will be no wrong at all to any man, and there will be remayning on over-plus, which will amount to a vaſt ſumme of money, for the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:117922:32"/>States uſe. And you know that the publique good of a Nation, ought to be preferred before any particular intereſt. But me thinks I hear ſome impropriators ſay to themſelves, I have a good bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and my meanes comes in with very little labour and coſt, and muſt I leave this good bargain? yea, I tell thee thou muſt leave it, and if thou haſt thy money it coſt, thou haſt no wrong at all, and if ſo be thou didſt purchaſe me to be thy ſlave in the time of ignorance, as to have the tenth of my labours, and not only of mine but of all my familie beſides, the tenth of my ſtock, and the tenth of all my encreaſe, yet this I know that the bargain hath been made void ever ſince the late Kings head was taken off; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we have been kept in this ſlavery and bondage many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years by an arbitrary power of Kings ſucceſſively, yet now the people are come to be a knowing people, and expect liberty and freedome from ſuch bonds. Therefore my Councell and adviſe, ſhall be once more to you Rulers and Governours, to whom the Nation have intruſted, and have committed all to your care to do them juſtice, that you will ſpeedily put theſe things into practiſe, and ſee it effectually performed, not having your ſpirits inſlaved with any ſelf-intereſt, nor to fear the rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thunders of the <hi>Clergie</hi> crying out againſt you, nor the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of any Lawyer, or Impropriator, nay fear not to do juſtice, though all the Devils in hell were againſt you, for God will own you, and he hath raiſed up a gallant Army to back you in all your juſt undertakings, againſt the violence of men. This is good Councel if you can take it, but if ſo be you ſlight and neglect it, God will find out a deliverance for his people, as once he did for the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who were held in ſore ſervitude and ſlave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eight years under <hi>Cuſhan-Riſhathaim, King of Meſopotamia, Judg.</hi> 3. Yet the Lord found out a diliverer, even among themſelves: <hi>Othniel</hi> ſlew the King of <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi> and ſo ſet the people at liberty. And here you may ſee a paralel to this in our late King, who could not be contented to govern his Kingdomes according to law and juſtice, but muſt uſurpe a power to himſelf over both people and lawes contrary to his oath, and ſo became a Tyrant, exerciſing do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over the people according to his arbitrary will, taking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf Gods own peculiar, and ſitting in his Throne, exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his Kingly power by monopolies and patents, contrary to his
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:117922:32"/>laws; and impoſing great burdens and taxes upon the people, as by <hi>Ship-money, Coat and Conduct-money</hi> &amp;c. Inſomuch that the burdens were grievous, inſupportable; and the people held in bondage and ſlavery, and laboured to keep them ſo: ſtrengthning himſelf by his wicked councel, and raiſ'd up a wicked Army to deſtroy his good councell. Yet the Lord found a way of deliverance for his people from that ſlavery and bondage wherein they were held; hence I draw this concluſion.</p>
               <p>That he that hath a limitted power ought not to exerciſe domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. But Gods power is only arbitrary, he governs according to his own will, therefore not to be limitted, but mans power is derived from Gods power, and hath its limits and bounds ſet: now if ſo be man comes to break theſe bounds, and comes to exerciſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, then he derogats from that power which was given, and attributes to himſelf that power which was not given, and ſo coms to be a rebel and a traitor againſt God and man: which was pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pably ſeen in the late King, and that ſcripture is fulfilled in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.23. <hi>Thy Princes are rebellious, and companions of theeves. every one loveth gifts, and followeth after rewards, they judge not the fatherleſſe, neither doth the cauſe of the widow come unto them.</hi> And was not the late King a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion of theeves and robbers, plunderers in the beſt ſence? And what complaints did he hear at any time, that were brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him? <hi>Therefore ſaith the Lord, the Lord of hoſts, the mighty God of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael: Ah! I will eaſe me of mine adverſaries, and avenge me of mine enemies</hi> verſe 24. <hi>and I will turn my hand upon thee, and purely purge away thy dreſſe, and take away all thy tin.</hi> verſe 25. <hi>and I will reſtore thy Judges as at the firſt, and Councellers as at the beginning &amp;c.</hi> verſe 26. And now me thinks I ſee Monarchie to be clearly extirpated, and rooted out of theſe three Nations, never to have a being any more, as to reign; and all earthly powers ſhaken throughout the whole world, and a perfect reſtauration at hand. For before Kings, there were <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Councellours,</hi> yet I never read of priority amongſt them. And if we look upon the computation of time, from the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto <hi>Noah</hi> you ſhall find it to be 1656. years. And from <hi>Noah</hi> to Chriſt coming in the fleſh was 3000. and od years. And from Chriſt coming in the fleſh to this preſent day, is 1650. So that I gather that the reſtauration is at hand. But of that day and hour knoweth no man, no not the Angels of Heaven, but my Father
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:117922:33"/>only. But as the daies of <hi>Noah</hi> were, <hi>ſo ſhall alſo the coming of the Son of man be,</hi> and if you compare this Scripture <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. with that of <hi>Gen.</hi> 5. then you may give me your thoughts concerning my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion. Not that I dare limit God in his time, but for ought I know this may be the very year of <hi>Jubilee.</hi> Therefore my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel and adviſe is to all Chriſtians, who make profeſſion of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and are placed in authority over us, that you exerciſe no ſuch Kingly, or Tyrannical power over us, which if ye do, it muſt be deſtroyed in you, or elſe you will be deſtroyed in it. For the Lord will find out a way of deliverance to his people from all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and cruelty.</p>
               <p>And now friends, my Counſel ſhall be to the Nation in Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, that you will ſubmit, and yield ſubjection to this preſent Government, and that for conſcience ſake. Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher powers, for there is no power but of God &amp;c. Now I know that many of you heretofore ſcrupled at the Covenant, and many of you at the Engagement, ſome out of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of conſeience, and ſome out of ſtubborneſſe and obſtinacy, which is a kind of rebellion, and cauſeth contention and ſtrife amongſt us. And here <hi>I</hi> ſaw, that the Clergie (eſpecially in the weſtern parts) had the chiefeſt hand againſt the engagement, and ſome of them pretended out of pure zeal, in regard they had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly taken the Covenant, as if the Engagement had claſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Covenant. But truly friends I am ſatisfied in my own ſpirit, without any ſcrupling at all. I have taken the covenant, I have taken the engagement, which engagement is to maintain this preſent Government, <hi>as it is now eſtabliſhed without a King or houſe of Lords,</hi> and we ought to be obedient thereunto, for we ſee, that God pulleth down, and he raiſeth up: he pulls down one power, and ſetteth up another. God hath ſet up this power over us, and it ſhall ſtand as long as he pleaſeth, and when he will have it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, it ſhall be deſtroyed notwithſtanding all the engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the vvorld, he vvill daſh it in peeces as he did the late Kings povver.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But the Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> ſaith, Bleſſed be the Lord thy God that hath ſet thee to do juſtice and judgement. Then ought vve to be obedient to this preſent government, although they ſhould command us unjuſt commands.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:117922:33"/>
               <p>My anſvver vvas yea, vve ought to yeeld obedience unto them, let their commands be vvhat they vvill, in caſe there be no povver to reſiſt thoſe unlavvful commands, but if ſo be God vvill raiſe a povver to reſiſt unlavvful commands, then tis lavvful to do it: For vvhether is it better to obey God or man judge ye. And I ſhall inſtance in the caſe of that late King, vvhere he commanded the people unlavvful and unjuſt commands. The Lord raiſed up a Parliament and Army to reſiſt thoſe unlawfull commands, and ſo deſtroy'd both him and his power. But if ſo be, thoſe that are placed in authority overs us, do not do juſtice and judgement. It is becauſe they cannot, why, becauſe they derogate from that power which is given; and atribute to themſelves that power, which is not given (as I ſaid before) yet notwithſtanding, we ought to yeeld obedience unto them, and wait Gods leaſure, for the hearts of Kings are in his hands, and he can turn them at his pleaſure, therefore wait upon God, his time is the beſt time, and in his due time he will accompliſh his own work, and ſatisfie all intereſts. But in the 2. <hi>Pſalm</hi> its ſaid, <hi>That the Kings of the earth ſtand up, and the Rulers take Counſel together againſt the Lord and againſt his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed.</hi> And truly friends, we have ſeen aboundance of great Counſels, many plots and contrivance, but moſt of them tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to advance ſelfe-intereſt, have we not ſeen abundance of pride and ſelf-loftineſſe? eſpecially, amongſt ſuch as are in high places both majeſterial and Military, aboundance of ſelf-ſeeking not only to make themſelves great, but their freinds alſo. This man hath a freind and he muſt have a great Office for him, that man hath a freind, and he muſt help him to ſome great preferment too &amp;c. and all to make themſelves rich upon the peoples ruins by oppreſſion and crueltie.</p>
               <p>And now freinds, I cannot forgit to ſpeak ſome thing more of the over-flowing pride of this Nation, not only amongſt the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, but amongſt all ſorts of people, as well the Clergie as others, For the Biſhops wore great laune ſleeves, and our Clergie weres as much upon their legs as they did upon their armes, with their Bootes ruffled down, with their tops upon the very Inſteps, and poor creatures I pitty them, that they do not ſee their down-fall to be ſo neer at hand. You know that the <hi>Scots</hi> were the firſt that pull'd down their Biſhops and ſet themſelves up in their room,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:117922:34"/>and then ſent a pattern of their directory to our Clergie that they might practiſe by their example; our Clergie being pretty act Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, they quickly learnt this leſſon, only altering the form of the directory, but not the ſubſtance, and ſo pull'd down the Biſhops here, and ſtept up into their room, and preſently in all haſt muſt have a claſſicall government ſet up, for all men to be compelled to worſhip ſo many Idols. Now I heard laſt night that the Kirk in <hi>Scotland</hi> lies very ſick of four ſore deadly wounds, the head, the hands, the heart, and the feet, and wait for a good hour, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of this tranſitory life: and me thinks it were not amiſſe for ſome good body to ſet the paſſing-bell going for our Clergie, for they are going the way of all fleſh too; for they are greeviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wounded in their hands too. <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.6. <hi>And if you aske them, what theſe wounds are, they ſhall anſwer thoſe with which, they were woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the houſe of their freinds:</hi> Now the time is near at hand that all Prophecies muſt be fulfilled, as that in <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.31. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.1, 2. that in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> but I have forgot the place, but the words are theſe, <hi>Who look to their own way, every one for his own advantage, and for his own purpoſe:</hi> this is fulfilled, and ſo is this of <hi>Micah</hi> 3. <hi>who byte with their teeth, and cry peace &amp;c.</hi> and that in <hi>Zech.</hi> 13. will be fulfilled e're long, <hi>they ſhall be aſhamed of their viſions &amp;c.</hi> And the Apoſtle ſpeaks much to this purpoſe in divers places, as that in the <hi>Theſ.</hi> he ſpeaks of ſuch as comes with all decievableneſſe of unrighteouſneſſe. And that in the <hi>Gal.</hi> ſuch as make a fair ſhew in the fleſh. And in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, he ſpeakes of ſuch as are decieving and being decieved. And in another place, ſuch as are holy in converſation, like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the falſe Apoſtles, which Scriptures points out notably to this purpoſe. And truly friends I muſt tell you, that all your holyneſſe, all your purity, all yoor zeal, all your honeſtie, nay all your, righteouſneſſe too: all muſt be burnt up, for it is ſaid <hi>accept your righteouſneſſe exceed the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees, ye ſhall in no wiſe enter into the Kingdome of Heaven.</hi> And truly for my part I cannot ſee, that any of your righteouſneſſe doth exceed theirs: for if we look upon the pureſt of you, we ſhall ſee aboundance of pride and ambition, aboundance of ſelf-righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſelf-purity, ſelf-holineſſe, ſelf-zel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> mixt with aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of coveteouſneſſe, and averice, aboundance of hatred and malice, eſpecially towards ſuch as are contrary to you in judgment.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:117922:34"/>
               <p>Object. <hi>But are all the Clergie a like with you? do you make no difference of miniſters? are there not abundance of Godly, faithfull, religious Preachers, faithfully diſpencing the word of God and with abundance of zeal?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer yea they are all alike with me, although ſome are more religious, more zealous, more holy then other, and although the Scripture faith, that the righteous, is more excellent then his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, yet I make no difference of the perſons of men, for if God be no reſpector of perſons, I know not why I ſhould: but for my part, I love them all very well, but not one better then another; and although ſome of them are accounted more glorious lights then others, yet they ſhal fall as the ſtars of heaven fell unto the earth <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. even as a figtree, caſteth her untimely figs &amp;c. That is not thoſe figs which naturally are brought forth alone by virtue of its pure <hi>ſap</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, but I conceive, by untimely figs is ment, all the righteouſneſſe of man which he with out or before Chriſts time of his riſing up in the branches, hath brought forth of himſelf, which is untimely, and therefore muſt fall to the ground and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come dung (as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of all his) for there is no righteouſneſs at that day can ſtand to endure, or paſſe through that refiners fire, but alone the righteouſneſſe and purity of himſelf, nor no garmant made by man, though it appear never ſo glorious now, that will endure the ſcouring with that fullers ſope, but will preſently be diſcovered to be but earthly and ſo conſumed and brought to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: friends in a word, at that day (which truly for my part I believe is neer at hand) there is no glory or excellency of man but will be extinguiſhed and put out (ſuch will be the glory of the coming of the Son of man) even as the moon and ſtars flie at the appearing of the Sun.</p>
               <p>And whereas I had ſome thoughts to ſpeak largely concerning the pride of Women in their fantaſtical apparel, and their fooliſh orn aments and dreſſings in their atyre, their chaines, and their bracelets, and their Mufflers, their Changable ſuits of apparel, and the Mantles and the wimples, and the criſping pins &amp;c. but becauſe of their weakneſſe, I ſhall trouble my ſelf no more at this time with a company of fooliſh women; but I ſhall refer them to that Scripture, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.24. Where they may read what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of them. But I know I ſhall be apt to ly under the ſenſure of many, why I ſhould undertake to medle with ſuch things as to give Counſel &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:117922:35"/>
               <p>What though there is abundance of injuſtice, what though there is aboundance of pride and ſelf-loftines, what though there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of ſelfiſhneſſe, and ſetting up ſelf-intereſt, <hi>what though you make Idols of Silver, Idols of Gold, and worſhip the works of your own hands, what though you make your ſelves ſtrong with engagements, what though you ſtrengthen your ſelves with a bond of Iron and braſſe,</hi> Dan. 4. but yet I muſt tell ye, all this will ſtand you but in little ſtead, when once the day of the Lord ſhall come upon you. Then there ſhall be nothing but pure juſtice, and no pride nor ſelf-loftineſſe at all. <hi>For the lofty looks of men ſhall be humbled, and the haughtineſſe of men ſhall be bowed down, and the Lord alone ſhall be exalted in that day-for the day of the Lord of beſts ſhall be upon every one that is proud and lofty, and upon every one that is lifted up and he ſhall he brought low.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In that day a man ſhall caſt his Idols of ſilver, and his Idols of gold, which they made each one for himſelf, to worſhip, to the moles, and to the bats:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To go into the clefts of the rocks, and into the tops of the ragged rocks, for fear of the Lord, and for the glory of his Majeſty; when he ariſeth to ſhake terrible the earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ceaſe ye from man whoſe breath is in his noſtrils, for wherein is he to be accounted of?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
